<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the best kinde of confessors by which preists [sic] in England may see how they may be, and lay Catholiks see how they may chuse the best kinde of confessors / composed by the most reverend father in God, Richard, bishop of Chalcedon, pastor of the Catholike in England.</title>
            <author>Smith, Richard, 1566-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93388</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43753</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475195</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475195</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151350</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93388)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151350)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2256:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the best kinde of confessors by which preists [sic] in England may see how they may be, and lay Catholiks see how they may chuse the best kinde of confessors / composed by the most reverend father in God, Richard, bishop of Chalcedon, pastor of the Catholike in England.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Richard, 1566-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>143 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed An. 1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Confession --  Catholic Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Confessors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151350:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151350:1"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF THE BEST KINDE OF CONFESSORS, By which Preiſts in England may ſee how they may be, and lay Catholiks ſee how they may chuſe the beſt kinde of Confeſſors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Compoſed by the moſt Reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God,</hi> RICHARD <hi>Bishop of Chalcedon, Paſtor of the Catholike in England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. Thimothe 5. v. 17.</bibl> 
               <hi>The Preiſts that rule wel let them be eſteemed worthie of duble honor.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Can. Qui vult de Poenitent. D. 6.</bibl> 
               <hi>who wil confeſs, let him confeſs, To the beſt Preiſt he can.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Printed An. 1651.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:151350:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151350:2"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF THE BEST KINDE OF CONFESSORS. Preſented to the vertuous Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minariſt, and Regular Prieſts, and Catholiks in England.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>REVEREND PRIESTS,</hi> both Seminariſts, and Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and beloued Lay Catholiks in England, my intention in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing this ſim all Treatiſe of the best kinde of Confeſſors, is not to diſparrage any kinde of Confeſſor allowed and approued by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, and much leſſe to abridge anie of their Faculties, or libertie to heare the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb facs="tcp:151350:3"/> and abſolue whomſoeuer come to them: but leauing all Prieſts with all faculties and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of confeſsing, which they haue, onely to shew ſuch Prieſts, as deſire, by being Confeſſors, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the greater glorie of God, the greater good and merit to their owne ſouls, and the greater ſpirituall profit to the ſouls of their Penitents, what kinde of Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors they ought to be, for to procure this. And in like manner, my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is not, to abridge in anie ſorte the libertie which Lay Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks haue to confeſs to what kinde of approued Priest they will or to put them to more charges of maintayning Priests, or to bring them to more danger of the lawes by vſing ſuch as I propoſe to them: but leauing them with all the libertie to confeſſ, to what kinde of approued Priest they will,
<pb facs="tcp:151350:3"/> and to contribute no more to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of more Priests, then they doe, onely to propoſe vnto them, what kinde of Priests are beſt for them, for the greater glorie of God, and greater ſpirituall good of their ſouls, leauing it (as I ſayd) free to their choyſe, whether they will vſe them, or no, or contribute par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to their maintenance, or no. By which meanes, they may haue both ſuch Conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſors as they haue, and allſo better ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors then they haue had allmoſt theſe hundred yeares. For it hath euer ſeemed to me a lamentable caſe of English Catholicks, that whereas Catholicks in Catholick countryes, and allſo in Zeland, and Holland, haue two kindes of approued Confeſſors, to wit, ſuch as huue paſtorall Charge of the ſouls of their Penitents, and ſuch allſo, as haue not that pastorall
<pb facs="tcp:151350:4"/> charge, but onely lawfull power to abſolue them, Catholickes in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glad (allmoſt theſe hundred <note place="margin">Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nd allmoſt theſe hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred yeares haue wanted Prieſts with charge of ſouls</note> yeares) haue had but one kinde, to witt, Confeſſors without paſtor all charge oſ ſouls, and haue wanted ſuch Confeſſors, as should haue had ſuch charge of their ſouls, which (as I shall shew clearly) were the far better kinde of Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and more needfull to Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, eſpecialy of the peorcr ſorie, who are not able to maintaine peculiar Prieſts, and yet for whoſe good, Confeſſors were equally inſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituted by God. And howſoeuer ſome will deny, that Confeſſors with paſtorall charge of ſouls, are better for the good of Penitents, then Confeſſors, who haue no ſuch charge none can deny but that it is better for the good of Penitents, that there be Confeſſors with charge of ſouls, then that there
<pb facs="tcp:151350:4"/> be none; and that there be more kindes of Confeſſors, which they may chuſe, then that there be but one kinde, eſpecially when they may haue them both without any reſtraint of their libertie, to vſe whether they will, and with no more danger or charges to them. And particulerly, this will be better for the poerer ſorte of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, who shall hereby haue ſuch Confeſſors, as shall be bound to adminiſter Sacraments vnto them, in what danger of ſickneſs, or war ſoeuer, which ſacraments ſometimes they haue wanted, for want of ſueh Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſors. For my part, I am fully of opinion of the Catechiſine ad Parochos, <hi>cap. De Poenitentiae Sacramento, ſect. 32.</hi> eompoſed by order of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent, and ſett forth by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Sea Apoſtolick, that <hi>what holines, pietie and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb facs="tcp:151350:5"/> remaineth in the Church, is in great part to be attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Confeſſion,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for I make this Treatiſe of the beſt kinde of Confeſſors, and intend (God willing) to make the like Treatiſe of the beſt Penitent. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps there neuer was in the Church, more frequenting of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, then of late hath been, but whether, it be for the fault of Confeſſors, or of Penitents, or of both, there doth not appeare ſuch amendement of life, as iuſtly may be expected of the greater frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of this ſacrament, and which (without doubt) it would effect, if it were frequented in ſuch ſorie, as it should be.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151350:5"/>
               <head>FIRST CHAPTER. The trw ſtate of the queſtion, Concerning the best kinde af Confeſſors, plainly ſett down.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE be two kindes of lawfull Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, the one hath paſtorall charge of the ſouls of his Penitents, the other, hath no ſuch charge. <note n="a" place="margin">S. Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pauper. Chriſti p. 422.. S. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas 2. 2. q. 188. art. 4. Bellar. l. 2. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chis. c. 45. Rodri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques to. 1. q. 35. art. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Now the queſtion is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe two kindes of Confeſſors, is, (of it ſelf) the better, that is, more for the glorie of God, more for the ſpirituall good, and merit of the Confeſſor himſelf, and alſo for the greater ſpirituall profit of the Penitents ſouls I ſay (of it ſelf) becauſe I conſider theſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151350:6"/> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fferent functions, onely in themſelues, abſtracting from the different perſons, in which they are, and alſo fron their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent qualities, of learning, vertue diſcretion, and ſuch like, or (if you will) ſuppoſing theſe two different kindes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, to be equall, or not much vnequall, for learning, vertue, diſcretion, and ſuch, like qualities, fitt to be in the perſons of lawfull Confeſſors. And theſe two different Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors <note place="margin">Inwhat all good Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</note> agree in that, that both are approued of the Church, both haue lawfull power or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to abſolue their Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, and the abſolution of both is valid and vndoubted, and allſo both ought to receiue their functions, and. execute them for the loue of God, and good of their Penitents; but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151350:6"/> they differ in manie other and weightie points, as shall herea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fter appeare, for which the one kinde is iuſtly to be preferred before the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>SECOND CHAPTER. That the comparing of the ſayd two different kindes of Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, ought not to be offenſiue to anye good Prieſt, or Catholick, but rather gratefull.</head>
               <p>THat the comparing of the two ſaid kindes of Confeſſors, ought not to be offenſiue to anye good. Prieſt or Catholik, is euident. Firſt, becauſe (as I ſayd) I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <note place="margin">I.</note> onely the ſayd different functions in themſelues, not touching any perſons or ſtate of Preiſts. Secondly, becauſe <note place="margin">II.</note> it much importeth both for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151350:7"/> Prieſts and Catholiks to know what kinde of Confeſſors are the beſt, that both, they may become the beſt kinde of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, and theiſe, vſe the beſt. Thirdly, becauſe Diuines <note place="margin">III.</note> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">S. Thom. 2. 2. q. 187. art. 8.</note> vſually compare the ſtates of Curats, and regulars, without offence of anye: of which compariſon, thus wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Suarez: tom. 3. de relig. lib. 1. c. 18. <hi>It is blameleſſ, if it be wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and modeſtly handled, and it be</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon o' Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, beſſ, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue then the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of Curats and Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</note> 
                  <hi>conſidered, that the compariſon is made, not between their perſons or deſcrts, but between their ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es and conditions, or, as S. Thomas ſpeaketh, the compariſon is made for the kinde of the worke, not for the charitie of the worker, as Chriſt Luke</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>preferreth the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue life, before the actiue.</hi> And yet this compariſon of Curats and Regulars, is not made for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151350:7"/> the greater good of a third, as we compare the ſayd different Confeſſors for the greater good of the Penitents, but meerly to shew, which of their ſtates is in it ſelf, better and perfecter. If therefor this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of different kindes of Confeſſors, be handled diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly and modeſtly (as it shall be of me) it will be more bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meles, then that of Curats and Regulars. Fourthly, becauſe <note place="margin">IV.</note> all ſorts of Prieſts in Countryes that are not Catholik (as En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland is not) or in Countryes, Where there is great ſcarcitye of Prieſts, as in the Indyes, are capable of both theſe fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Confeſſors; and ſome Regulars <note n="a" place="margin">S. Thom. 2. 2 q. 184. art. 7.</note> are, euen in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik Countryes, and where there is no ſcarcitie of Prieſts, Confeſſors with charge of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151350:8"/> ſouls, as others are withont ſuch charge. And if Regular Prieſts in England, will vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the burden, they may haue paſtorall charge of their Penitents ſouls, as well as others, Fiftly, becauſe no man carefull of his health, would be offended to haue shewed vnto him, what kinde of Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon or Phyſitian, to witt, a Galleniſt, or Paracelſian, is better for him, and why should any Penitent carefull of the good of his ſoule, take it ill, that the like should be shewed to him of his ſpirituall Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, who is his Confeſſor? If therefor any take it ill, that it be shewed, what kinde of Confeſſor is the beſt for the glorie of God, and good of ſouls, he sheweth therereby, that he is not deſirous of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151350:8"/> greater glory of God, and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpirituall profitt of ſouls, of which I hope no good Prieſt, or Catholik in England, is guiltie. Laſtly becauſe I, being Paſtor of the Catholiks in England, as P. Vrban VIII. in his Breue to me An. 1626. in expres termes calleth me, ought to shew them al the beſt means I can, for the good of their ſoules, and in doing ſo, none can be iuſtly offended, for I doe but may dutie, and what I am bound to doe. And alſo (though vnworthie) I am one of thoſe of whome our Sauiour ſaid: who heareth you, heareth me, who deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:151350:9"/>
               <head>THIRD CHAPTER. That it much importeth, both Priests, and Lay Catholiks, to know, which is the best kinde of Confeſſors.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THat it greatly impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Prieſts, for to know, which is the beſt kinde of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, is euident. Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thereby they may know, what kinde of Confeſſors are moſt pleaſing to God, doe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit more to themſelues and do alſo more good to their Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents. Secondly, becauſe Prieſts are diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſers of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of God, and it impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them to know, who are the beſt diſpenſers of ſuch great matters. Thirdly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Confeſſors are ſpirituall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151350:9"/> Phyſitians of their Penitents, and it much importeth Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, both for themſelues, and for their Patients, to be the moſt able to cure their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients,</p>
               <p n="2">2. That it alſo greatly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth Penitents, to know who are the beſt kinde of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, is likewiſe euident. Firſt, becauſe (as is ſayd) Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors are their ſpirituall Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, who muſt cure their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall diſeaſes. Secondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Church counſeleth her children to chuſe the beſt kinde of Confeſſor they can, De Paenitent. D. 1. c. 88. and d. 6. c. 1. where Nauarre in C. <hi>Placuit,</hi> ſayth: <hi>The meaning of the Canon is, to counſel, that by what way ſoeuer a Penitent can iuſtly, he should ſeek the beſt Priests.</hi> See him there §. <hi>Quod
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151350:10"/> autem.</hi> Thirdly, becauſe (as is a foreſayd) the Church pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, that one of the beſt meanes she hath to keep men from vice, and to driue them to vertue, is Confeſſion and ſurely the beſt meanes to the beſt Confeſſion, is the beſt kinde of Confeſſor, as t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e beſt meanes to be cured is to gett the beſt Phyſitian.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>FORTH CHAPTER. That a Confeſſor, who hath Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorall charge of the ſouls of Penitents, is better, then one, who hath no ſuch charge, proued by their different Inſtitutors.</head>
               <p>THe firſt proof, that à Confeſſor, who hath pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorall charge of ſouls, is, <hi>caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris paribus,</hi> better, then one who hath no ſuch charge, I will
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151350:10"/> take from their different Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutors. For Chriſt himſelfe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly inſtituted Confeſſors with paſtorall charge of ſouls, as is euident out of S. Iohn chapt. 20. v. 23. where he ſayth to his Apoſtles, and in them to their ſucceſſors. <hi>Take the Holy Ghoſt, whoſe ſinns you shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt they are remitted; and whoſe you shall retaine, they are retained.</hi> Now the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles were, and their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors are, Confeſſors with paſtorall charge of ſouls. But that Chriſt immediatly inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Confeſſors without char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of ſouls, we neither finde in ſcripture, nor in Tradition: but theiſe were inſtituted by the Church, as S. Thomas teacheth in theſe words 22. q. 188. art. 4. <hi>It was requiſit, that beſide the ordinary Prelats, others
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151350:11"/> should be aſſumed to ſuch offices.</hi> Where he doth not ſay, that Confeſſors without charge of ſouls were neceſſary, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly requiſit, nor that they were immediatly inſtituted by Chriſt, as ordinary Prelats are, but aſſumed, to witt, by the Church. Secondly, becauſe Chriſt inſtituted no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors but the Apoſtles and the 72. Diſciples: but both theiſe, doubtles had charge of ſoules. And ſurely, that kinde of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor is (of himſelf, and <hi>caeteris paribus)</hi> better, who is imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly inſtituted by God, and with whome God will more concurre, then that kinde of Confeſſor, who is not ſo inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted. For it cannot be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but that he will more concurre with ſuch kinde of Confeſſors, as himſelf imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151350:11"/> inſtituted, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſuch, as are inſtituted by others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>FIFTH CHAPTER. That a Confeſſor with charge of ſoules, is better, then one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch charge, proued by the different ends of their Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</head>
               <p>THat a Confeſſor with charge of ſoules, is (of himſelf and <hi>caeteris paribus)</hi> better, then one without ſuch charge, I proue by the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ends for which they were inſtituted For Confeſſors with charge of ſouls, were inſtituted for themſelues, as neceſſary of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiers for the remiſſion of mens ſinns, as is euident by Chriſts words cited in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer chapter. For Chriſt hauing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151350:12"/> inſtituted the Sacrament of Pennance, he muſt needes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute purpoſely officers for the adminiſtring thereof, as were the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors. But Confeſſors without charge of ſouls, were not inſtituted purpoſely and for themſelues; but by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and for ſome other cauſe, to witt, as S. Thomas <note n="a" place="margin">2. 2. q. 188. art. 4.</note> ſayeth, in the place cited in the former chapter, <hi>for the multitude of the faithfull, and for the difficulty of finding ſufficient perſons for all people.</hi> And the ſame ſay Alber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Magnus, and S. Bonauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, cited by Dionyſius Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſianus in 4. d. 17. q. 6. and it is euident. But doubtles, thoſe Confeſſors, are (of themſelues, and <hi>caeteris paribus)</hi> better, that is, more for the glorie of God, and good of ſouls, who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151350:12"/> immediatly by God himſelf, and purpoſely for themſelues, as proper mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Sacrament of pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, then thoſe, who are inſtituted of the Church, nor yett nether purpoſely for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but for other occaſions, and if which occaſions had not been, would neuer haue been inſtituted, as none ſuch were inſtituted til about ſome foure hundred years agoe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>SIXT CHAPTER. That a Confeſſor with charge of fouls, is better, then one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, proued by Gods binding to Confeſs to the one, and not to the others.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe third proof, that a Confeſſor with charge
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151350:13"/> of the ſoule of his Penitents, is better, that is, more for the glorie of God, and good of ſouls, then a Confeſſor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch charge, I will take from that God bindeth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to the one, and not to the other. For that God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to confeſs our ſinns to ſome kinde of Confeſſors, I ſuppoſe as a point of Fayth. And he hauing inſtituted Confeſſors with charge of ſouls, and none without ſuch charge, as I shewed before, his command muſt needs be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of Confeſſors with charge of ſouls, and not of others. For the Councel of Trent. ſeſſ. 14. c. 5. and all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, doe inferre, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt inſtituted the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſors, Iudges of ſinns, for to remitt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151350:13"/> retain them, therewithall he bound men to confeſs their ſinns to them, becauſe they could not iudge of whar they knew not. But he did not binde vs to confeſs to ſuch, as himſelf did not inſtitute iudges of ſinns. And hereupon Sotus in 4. diſt. 18. q. 4. art. 2. ſayth <hi>The Canon</hi> (of yeatly Confeſſion to ones proper Prieſt who hath care of ſouls) <hi>did but add the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to ones proper Prieſt.</note> 
                  <hi>yearly time to the diuine command. And it would neuer haue reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned confeſsion to a proper Prieſt, vnleſs it had vnderſtood, that it was a diuine precept, and allwayes obſerued in the Church.</hi> And he addeth ibide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>That this reſtraint to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſs to ones proper Prieſt, is eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall.</hi> So plainly he ſayeth, that to confeſs to ones proper Prieſt who hath charge of ſoules, is diuine, and Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151350:14"/> Bellarmin allſo lib. 3. de Poenitent. c. 13. anſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ering to this obiection of Caluin: the obligation of Confeſſion is but humain; becauſe it was made in the Councell of Lateran, ſayeth; <hi>That the Councell did onely determin the time:</hi> and if all that command of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſing to ones proper Prieſt, be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, beſide the time, then obligation if ſelf to confeſs to ones. Proper Prieſt, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine. And if it be a diuine precept to confeſs to ones pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Prieſt; who hath charge of ſouls, and not to confeſs to an other, who hath not ſuch charge of ſouls, ſurely it is of itſelf better to confeſs to him, then to anie other, becauſe in confeſſing to him, we doe an act of obedience to Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which we doe not, in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151350:14"/> confeſſion to others, to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he commandeth vs not to confeſs. And obedience is ſo gratefull to God, as he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth <note place="margin">a 1. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> it before ſacrifice. And it were a maruell, if anie who exhorte to obedience to man, should dehorte from obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If any obiect, that if it be a diuine precept, to confeſs to ones proper Prieſt, that then it will follow, that cuer more we muſt confeſs to him, and neuer to others. I anſwer, that this will not follow, becauſe though God commandeth vs to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſs to our proper Prieſts, yet he fobiddeth not vs to confeſs to others, when there is iuſt cauſe: but it will follow, that we muſt not confeſs to others without iuſt cauſe, as diuines <note n="b" place="margin">Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre man.</note> teach. For diuine affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151350:15"/> precepts, doe binde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, <note place="margin">praelud. 9. Sotus l. 10. de Iure 43. arr. 1. Azon. tom. 2. lib. 7. c. 4. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. de Poe nit. c. 18.</note> but not for alwayes, to witt, when there is iuſt cauſe to the contrary. And which is iuſt cauſe, and where there is iuſt cauſs, pertaineth to the Church to determine, and to her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination we ought to ſtand, she being the pillar and ground of truth, and taught all truth by the Holy Ghoſt. And that she had iuſt cauſe to diſpenſe herein, appeareth by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd words of S. Thomas, that the multitude of Penitents was too great for to confeſſe onely to their proper Prieſts, and that it was hard to finde ſufficient proper Prieſts for all places. In which caſes (doubleſs) the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatiue diuine precept of confeſſing to proper Prieſts who haue charge of the ſouls of their Penitents, doth not binde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:151350:15"/>
               <head>SEVENTH CHAPTER. That is better for Penitents to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to Prieſts who haue charge of their ſouls, then to thers, proued by the ends for which God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted Conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſsion.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe fourth proof, that it is better for the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, to conſeſs to a Prieſt, who hath charge of his ſoul, then to others, I take from the ends, for which God inſtituted Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, of ſinns. For one eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall end, for which he inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Confeſſion, was, that ſuch as had charge of ſouls, might therby better know the eſtate of the ſouls, whereof they haue charge (as corporalle Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians know the eſtate of their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151350:16"/> Patients by their telling it) and thereby might be the better able to help them. And to this purpoſe, it is ſayd Prouerb. 27. <hi>Diligently know the face of thy sheep:</hi> whereupon S. Thomas opuſc. 18. c. 4. ſayeth; <hi>That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">A prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall end of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, is to be well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor.</note> 
                  <hi>to care of ſouls, which is ſayd Prouerb. 27. Diligently know the face of thy sheep, which eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially is done, by hearing Conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi> And Sotus in 4. d. 18. q. 4. art. 2. <hi>To Confeſs to ones proper priest is euangelicall and profitable to the ſouls of the people, that the Paſtor may know the sheep, as Chriſt ſayeth, and be knowne by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Ibid. <hi>Among the laws of feeding, that is an eſpeciall one, which is exerciſed in the ſacrament of pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</hi> And d. 20. q. 1. art 5. <hi>Seing the greateſt knowledge and iugement of the flock, is gotten by ſacramentall Confeſsion, in this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151350:16"/> ſacrament eſpecially, it is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, that it be free for euery one to goe to what Priest he will, but that euery one be bound to his proper Prieſt, ſo as he confeſs but to him, or to another, by his leaue.</hi> And lib. 10. de Iure &amp;c. q. 3. art. 1. <hi>It is the nature, care, and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a good Paſtor, that he and his sheep know well one an other.</hi> Azor. tom. 2. l. 7. c. 4. <hi>A Paſtor knoweth his sheep, and leadeth them to paſture, and sheep know the voyce of their Paſtor. A paſtor all ſo muſt goe before his flock, and know the face of his sheep. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth it onely belong to a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor to offer ſacrifice for his sheep, to preach and giue them the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but allſo he muſt watch vpon his flock, viſit his sheep and know their faces. Well ſayd Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon; Diligently know the face of thy sheep.</hi> Bellarmin. l. 3. de
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151350:17"/> Poenitent. c. 12. <hi>Pastors, by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, know the diſeaſes of their sheep, and by that meanes, can apply conuenient remedies to euery one in particular, and alſo, in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick ſermons, reprehend thoſe vices, to which they know their flock to be moſt ſubiect.</hi> And Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riquez de Poenit. l. 2. c. 16. <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, for to know the face of their sheep, may compell them to fullfill the precepts of yearly Confeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Communion.</hi> See Gamach de Paenitent. c. 18. n. 59. I add alſo. that the Councel of Trent. ſeſſ. 25. c. 1. ſayth. <hi>By diuine precept, all who haue charge of ſouls, muſt know their sheep.</hi> And the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trauagant C. <hi>Saluatos: Paſtors muſt ſee the faces of euery one.</hi> Out of all which it is euident, that by commandement of God, all Paſtors muſt diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know the faces of their
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151350:17"/> sheep; and alſo, that this dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent knowledge is cheefly got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by hearing their Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſo that, one end of the Penitents confeſſion, is to lett his Paſtor know the face and eſtate of his sheep. Which end they fullfill, who confeſs to their Paſtor; and they fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, who confeſs not to him, but to others. And doubtleſs, they doe better, who fullfill ſo cheef an end of confeſſion, then they, who fruſtrate it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. An other end of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, is shame or confuſion of our ſelues, which God would haue vs to vndergoe., both for to reſtrain vs thereby from ſinning, and allſo for to make thereby ſome ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to him, whome we dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honored and diſgraced by our ſinning. And commonly men
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151350:18"/> haue greater shame, to confeſs to their proper Prieſt, with whom they vſually conuerſe, then to others, whom they chuſe of themſelues, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liue not with them, or ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſee them. And shame in Conftſsion, is a great part of pennance, and of ſatisfaction for our ſinns, and a great bridle to committ them no more. P. <note place="margin">Shame a great part of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note> Innocent 4. C. <hi>Etſi animarum: Shame is a great parte of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</hi> P. Benedict. C. <hi>Inter cunctos: Shame is a great part of pennance.</hi> The Catechiſme ad Parochos cap. de Paenitent. ſect. 32, <hi>Shame of confeſsing, doth as it were bridle the deſire of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and withold wickedneſs.</hi> And Bellarmin. lib. 3. de Paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. c. 12. <hi>The shame which we ſuffer in confeſsing, is a part of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction.</hi> So that, by confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151350:18"/> where leſs shame is, we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minish one great end of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, which is to bridle vs from ſinne, and allſo one part of the ſacrament, which is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. And ſurely it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to fullfill a good end of confeſſion, and one part of the ſacrament of Pennance, then any way to diminish them. And this shame is like to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter potion, which a good Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent should not refuſe for the greater good of his ſoul, no more then he would refuſe a bitter potion for the greater health of his body. Nay it will bring him glory before any vertuous Confeſſor, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and his Angels, who <note place="margin">What shaine brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth glorie. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtici 4. v. 25.</note> reioyce att the repentance of a ſinnar. For (as the ſcripture ſayth) <hi>there is a shame or confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which bringeth glorie.</hi> And
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151350:19"/> this we ſee in S. Auguſtin, who is moſt admired for his publick Confeſſion of his ſinns, and that not to a Prieſt, but to all the world, and to all and to all poſterity till the worlds end. And beſides, true contrition <note place="margin">Loue of God, maketh bitter, ſwett.</note> for the loue of God, will turne all this bitterneſs into ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and make all God his yoke, ſwett, and his burden, light.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>EIGHT CHAPTER. That it is better to confeſs to a Priest, who hath charge of the Penitents ſoul, then to an other, proued by the Iudgement of the Church.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe fifth proof, that it is better to confeſs to a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151350:19"/> Prieſt, who hath charge of the Penitents ſoul, then to an other, who hath not that charge, I will take from the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the holy Church. which in that great Generall Councel of Lateran vnder P. Innocent 3. and after, by diuers graue and vertuous Popes, <note place="margin">The Church co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to confeſs to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Prieſts but not to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. P. Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent 3.</note> hath for many hundred yeares commanded all Catholicks of either ſex, to confeſs (att leaſt once a yeare) to their proper Prieſt who hath charge of their ſouls, but neuer commanded them to confeſs to ſuch as had no charge of their ſouls. <hi>Euery Chriſtian</hi> (ſayth the foreſayd Councel) <hi>of other ſex, after they are come, to yeares of diſcretion, shall truly confeſs all their ſinns to their proper Prieſt, at leaſt once a yeare.</hi> P. Martin 5. (in his Bull <note place="margin">P. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin 5.</note> related by P. Adrian 6. de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151350:20"/> q. 5. and others) <hi>we will, that thoſe who confeſs to Fryars, shall neuer the leſs be bound, to confeſs, att leaſt once a yeare, to their Parish Prieſt, as the great Councel ordaineth.</hi> And P. Sixtus <note place="margin">P Sixtus 4.</note> IV. in extrauagante, vices; de pace &amp; treuga, admonisheth Regulars, that <hi>they forbeare to preach, that Parishioners are not bound to confeſs, att leaſt att Eaſter, to their proper Prieſts, becauſe they are bound thereto by law.</hi> And that the foreſayd Councel, by a <hi>proper Prieſt,</hi> meaneth one, <note place="margin">A pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Prieſt, hath charge of ſouls.</note> that hath charge of ſouls, is manifeſt. Firſt, becauſe P. Martin 5. in his words cited ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth it of a <hi>Parish Prieſt,</hi> who (doubtleſs) hath charge of ſouls. Secondly, becauſe what Prieſt hath not charge of a Penitent, is not his proper Prieſt, but is common to all
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151350:20"/> Penitents whoſe confeſſions he heareth. Thirdly, becauſe as Sotus ſayth 4. d. 18. q. 4. art. 2. <hi>It is an abuſe, to call a delegate, a Proper Prieſt. For a proper Prieſt, is taken but one way, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Proper Prieſt is the ſame, that ordinary, to witt, he to whome, by his proper office and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, belongeth the charge of ſouls, and is iudge in the Court of conſcience.</hi> And againe: <hi>It is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">One shing to be a proper Prieſts, an other to be lawfull.</note> 
                  <hi>one thing, to be lawfull, an other to be proper, who is proper, is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary: but lawfull, euery one is, who can work either by his owne authority, or by commiſsion.</hi> And the like hath To let inſtruction is Sacerdotum lib. 3. c. 13. And Eſtius in 4. D. 17. §. 13. ſayth. <hi>There is but one acception of proper Prieſt, who hath proper and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary auctoritie to abſolue him, in reſpect of whome he is called proper
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151350:21"/> that is, to whoſe charge, each one is properly ſubiect.</hi> Laſtly, becauſe to call ſuch as hear confeſſions without charge of the ſouls of their Penitents, <hi>proper Prieſts,</hi> was but deuiſed for to shew, that Regulars did not heare confeſſions againſt the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd Canon of the Councel of Lateran, which shift is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, for though they be not proper Prieſts, they hear con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions by leaue of the Pope, and Bishops, and therefor no more offend againſt that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, then ſuch Prieſts doe, who hear Confeſſions by leaue of the Parish Prieſt. Moreouer P. Vrbain 2. in Canon. <hi>Placuit, <note place="margin">P. Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bain 2.</note> de Paenitentia</hi> D. 6. ordaineth thus: <hi>we will, that no Prieſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to confeſsion any, that is vnder the charge of an other, vnleſs it be for the ignorance of him, to whom
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151350:21"/> he confeſſed before.</hi> And P. Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. <note place="margin">P Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. XI.</note> XI. Can. inter cunctos: <hi>We stirctly command, that Fryars carefully admonish them whoſe Confeſsions they heare, and exhort in their ſermons, to confeſs to their Prieſts, att least once a yeare, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming that (doubtleſs) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>his is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</note> 
                  <hi>profitable to their ſouls.</hi> And this ſemeth to haue been the intent of the Councel of Trent, which ſeſſ 25. c. 13. comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>that where Parochiall</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Parish to be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Trent would haue confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to be made to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish Prieſts.</note> 
                  <hi>Churches haue no certain bounds, nor their Rectores certain people, whome to gouern, but indifferently minister ſacraments to ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them, the holy Synod com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth Byshops, for the greater ſaifty of ſouls committed to them, that the people being deuided into certain peculiar Parishes, they appoint to euery one their perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151350:22"/> and proper Parish Prieſt, who may know them, and of whom alone, they may lawfully receaue ſacraments, or prouide ſome other better way, as the condicion of the place requireth.</hi> And ſeſſ. 14. c. 9. <hi>Dioceſes and Parishes were most reaſonably diuided, and proper Pastors giuen to each flock, and Rectors of inferior Churches, who should haue euery one care of his sheep, that Eccleſiasticall order be not confounded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Neither is the foreſayd Canon of the Lateran Councel abrogated. For allbeit ſome ſay, that P. Leo X. hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that who confeſs to Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicants, doe ſatisfy the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſayd Canon; yett that declaration doth not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate the ſayd Canon, but rather sheweth, that it
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151350:22"/> bindeth ſtill, by ſaying, that men by confeſſing to Mendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants, <note place="margin">See Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cil. Tride<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. ſeſſ. 14. Can. 58. Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus 4. and Martin 5. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prá.</note> doe ſatisfy the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Canon, and onely sheweth, that the Mendicants hearing of Confeſſions by the Popes leaue, is not contrary to the obligation of that Canon, as other Prieſts hearing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions by leaue of the Parish Prieſt, are not contrary to the ſame. See more of this in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre in <hi>C. Placuit</hi> D. 6. n. 121. Gamach de Paenitent. c. 18. Henriquez de Paenitent. l. 2. c. 16. And though the ſayd Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non or law were abrogated, and did not binde now att all, that would no way weaken the force of my argument, taken from the iudgement of the Church. For she hauing both by a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councel, and allſo by Bulls of diuers Popes, ſeuerly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151350:23"/> commanded Catholicks to confeſs to Preiſts who haue charge of their ſouls, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer commanded them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to ſuch as haue no ſuch charge, but onely permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them ſo to doe by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (as S. Thomas ſayd) of the too great multitude of Penitents, of the inſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of ſome Prieſts who haue charge of ſouls, she clearly sheweth, that she iudgeth it (of it ſelf) better for Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, to confeſs to ſuch prieſts as haue charge of their ſouls, then to thoſe who haue not that charge. For (doubteleſs) she iudgeth that better for her children to doe, which she ſo often, ſo ſeuerely, and for ſo many ages hath commanded, them to doe, then that, which she neuer commanded them
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151350:23"/> to doe, nor perhaps would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt them to doe, if the too great multitude of penitents, and inſufficiency of many Prieſts who haue charge of ſouls, did not force her to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>NINTH CHAPTER. That it is better for Penitents, to confeſs to a Prieſt, who hath charge of their ſouls, then to others, proued by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe, who were Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Penitents without charge of ſouls.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IT is ſo euident, that (of itſelf) it is better for Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents to confeſs to Prieſts, who haue charge of ſouls, then to others, that euen the chei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt of thoſe, who were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151350:24"/> of Penitents without charge of their ſouls, doe acknowledge it to be better. S. Bonauenture a Doctor of <note place="margin">S Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture.</note> the Church, and Generall of the Franciſcans, writeth thus in 4. D. 17. q. 2. n. 108. <hi>I beleeue</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Euer good.</note> 
                  <hi>that if the Parish Prieſt be fitt, that it is euer good, that the Paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent be remitted to him, of whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he is heard.</hi> And num. 105. <hi>wherefore it is to be beleeued, that all Paris hioners whenſoeuer, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Are bound.</note> 
                  <hi>how often ſoeuer they confeſs to ſuch</hi> (Mendicants) <hi>are bound to confeſs to their proper Prieſts, if they be good and ſufficient, and exact it, and wil not otherwiſe be content. And this I ſay, at least once a yeare.</hi> Ibidem: <hi>And therefor it <note place="margin">Whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel.</note> is wholeſome Counſel, for all theiſe to be remitted to their proper Prieſts, that if they be not content with that Confeſsion, they be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151350:24"/> heard againe.</hi> Angelus, Vicar <note place="margin">Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</note> Generall of the ſayd Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, and Commiſſary to Pope Sixtus IV. in his Summe, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo, <hi>Confeſsio,</hi> 4. num. 33. <hi>It is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">I after for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> 
                  <hi>ſafer to confeſs to our owne Prieſt or Prelate, then to an other, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deceits and vnleawfulneſſes, which are in other Deputies. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I allways aduiſe, that none leaue his owne Parish Priest, for an other Deputy, vnleſs it clearly appeare, that he whome he hath choſen, be of good conſcience and ſufficient skill, and that more, then his owne Parish Priest. For if there be any defect in his owne Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish Prieſt, the Penitent is more excuſed in confeſsing to him then to an other, becauſe superiors in appointing him, doe ſeeme to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue him for ſufficient.</hi> Scotus <note place="margin">Scotus</note> the cheifeſt diuine among the ſame Franciſcans in 4. d. 5. q. 6.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151350:25"/> ſayeth. <hi>We should allwayes chuſe that</hi> (Confeſſor) <hi>caeteris paribus,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Caeteris par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bus.</note> 
                  <hi>to whome that belongeth by office.</hi> And Confeſſor by office, none is, but he, who hath charge of ſouls. Richardus de Media vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, <note place="margin">Richar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus de media villa.</note> an other great Franciſcan Doctor, in 4. D. 17. q. 1. <hi>Allbeit in ſome caſes it were better for one, to chuſe a Confeſſor as be would, then to be bound to confeſs to his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, yett it were not profitable</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Not profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity. S. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas.</note> 
                  <hi>for the Communitye, that it should be lawfull for euery one to chuſe his Confeſſor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. S. Thomas, an other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of the Church, and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Doctor of the Dominicans, in Supplemento q. 8. art. 5. ad 4. writeth thus: <hi>Werefore it is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">God.</note> 
                  <hi>good, that he, who heareth Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions by auctority of the Bishop, doe perſwade the Penitent, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to his proper Prieſt.</hi> Sotus a <note place="margin">Sotus.</note>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:151350:25"/> graue and learned Dominican, in 4. D. 20. q. 1. art. 5. <hi>The ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Paſtor of the Church cannot ſuficiently prouide for the whole Church, vnleſs he giue Bishops to all churches. Wherfore, ſeing the chiefeſt notice and iudgement of the flock, is gotten by ſacramentall confeſsion, it is requiſit, that eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit.</note> 
                  <hi>in this Sacrament, it be not free for euery one to runn to euery Prieſt, but that euery one be bound to his own, that he confeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not, but to him, or with his leaue.</hi> Nauar. <note place="margin">Nauar.</note> a Canon Regular, and famous Caſuiſt. Concil. 15. de Paeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia: <hi>I should thinck, that he did wiſely, who</hi> (att the houre of <note place="margin">W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſely.</note> death) <hi>procureth himſelf to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued of his Parish Priest there preſent, or of his ſuperior, rather then of others.</hi> Gabriel <note n="*" place="margin">Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel. Trithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius. Poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinus.</note> allſo a Regular in 4. D. 17. q. 2 art. 3. <hi>If all be a like, it is better to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151350:26"/> to ones proper Prieſt, as Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors commonly hold, as S. Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture, and Angelus in Summa,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Better for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> 
                  <hi>Confeſsio 3. §. 34. for many cauſes, and auoiding of dangers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Layman, a great writer, <note place="margin">Laiman Good of the Church</note> and Ieſuit l. 5. tract. 6. c. 33. <hi>Seing it is inſtituted for the common good of the Church, and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient gouernment, that all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full should confeſs to their proper Prieſt, that must not be limitted or restrained for priuate commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by priuate interpretation of Doctors, eſpetially becauſe many by this meanes, falſly pretending im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments of confeſsion, may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw themſelues from the iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their Paſtor.</hi> Reginald <note place="margin">Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nald.</note> an other Ieſuit lib. 1. n. 61. <hi>Well addeth Nauarre, that he shall do wiſely, who</hi> (att the <note place="margin">Wiſely.</note> houre of death) <hi>his Parish Prieſt or Superior being preſent,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151350:26"/> procureth to be abſolued of him, rather then of others.</hi> And as Barboſa writeth in Remiſſ. <note place="margin">Barbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa.</note> Concil. Tridentiniſeſſ. 14. c. 7. <hi>Nauarre Conſil. Is. ſub titulo Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiae, Sayrus</hi> (an English Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictin) <note place="margin">Sairus.</note> 
                  <hi>dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. 21. ſub eodem ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo, Reginald. l. 2. n. 60. ſay, that he should do wiſely, who if his Parish Prieſt or Superior be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, procured himſelf to be abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of him at the houre of death, rather then of an other.</hi> And him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf allegat. 25. num. 51. ſayeth: <hi>It is better to confeſs to ones Paſtor</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter, at the houre of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath.</note> 
                  <hi>att the houre of death, then to an other.</hi> And it if it be both wiſer and better, at the houre of death, to confeſs, to ones Paſtor or Superior, then to an other, it is much better and wiſer to doe ſo in life time. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is certain, as the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Trent, hash declared ſeſſ.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151350:27"/> 17. c. 7. <hi>that, att the houre of death, all Priests can abſolue any Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent from any ſinns or Cenſures,</hi> which all Prieſts cannot do, nay few Prieſts can doe, in time of life, and therefor their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution is not ſo certain in time of life, as in time of death. If therefor it be better and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer to be abſolued of ones Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish Prieſt or Superior, at time of death, when the abſolution by any Prieſt whatſoeuer, from what ſinns or cenſures ſoeuer, is moſt certain, much better and wiſer it is, to procure to be abſolued of him in life time, when all Prieſts abſolution is not ſo certain, as it is in time of death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:151350:27"/>
               <head>TENTH CHAPTER. That it is better for Penitents, to Confeſs to Priests, who haue charge of their ſouls, then to others, proued by the Generall practiſe of thoſe Priests, who are Confeſſors of Penitents, without charge of their ſouls.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe ſeuenth proof, that (of it ſelf) it is better for Penitents, to confeſs to ſuch Prieſts, as haue charge of their ſouls, then to others, shall be taken from the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall practiſe of ſuch Prieſts, as are Confeſſors of Penitents without charge of ſouls. For they doe not confeſs it in words onely (as we ſaw in the former Chapter) but much
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151350:28"/> more in practiſe and indeeds, becauſe they ſuffer not any of their owne compagnies, vpon any occaſion, to confeſs to whome they will, but onely to ſuch as they appoint for them. The Gloſſ. in Clement. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum. <hi>Religious men, according to the ſtatuts of their orders, muſt confeſs to their Prelats.</hi> Suarez tomo 4. de relig. l. 2. c. 16. <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall leaue to confeſs to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one will, Would deſtroy reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions.</note> 
                  <hi>it is, that by ordinary right, and without diſpenſation, regulars cannot confeſs to others, then to ſuch Confeſſors, as are apointed for them by their ſuperiors.</hi> Ibid. n. 6. <hi>Generall leaue, to chuſe ones confeſſor, would tend to great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment of religions, for it may be an occaſion of diſſolution and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xation of religious diſcipline.</hi> And num. 7. <hi>By ſuch generall licence and ordinarie vſe, religious diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline would be plainly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne.</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:151350:28"/> Henriquez l. 7. c. 22. §. 4. <hi>The Society of Ieſus kepeth that priuilege, that none, without the ſuperiors leaue, can chuſe a Confeſſor beſide him, who is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. And Gregorie the 13. granted this to the Society.</hi> Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man l. 5. tract. 6. c. 10. n. 20. <hi>By their proper statuts, it is not permitted, to religious to confeſs out of their owne order to any other, but to whom the Superior appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</hi> And Rodriquez to. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> q. 62. art. 4. and 5. reciteth the Bulls of Popes, which Ieſuits, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcans, Auguſtins, and other Religious orders, haue procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that none of theirs, euen in time of Iubilées, may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to any, but to ſuch as their Superiors appoint. And head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: <hi>This is very good and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</hi> And Petigian in Summa D. 17. q. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. art. 3. affirmeth, that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151350:29"/> there is excommunication <hi>latae ſententiae,</hi> that no religious, euen by vertue of a Bull, do conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs to any other, then to him, who is appointed by his ſuperior.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And doth ſuch great good come to religious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, by confeſſing to none, but to ſuch, as their ſuperiors appoint for them: and would no good come to the holy compagnie of Chriſt, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, if her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren confeſſed to ſuch as haue charge of their ſouls. Would ſuch great harme come to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious compagnies, as their vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſolution and relaxation of religious diſcipline by gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall leaue to confeſs to what ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued Prieſt they would, and will no hurt, no relaxation of eccleſiaſticall diſcipline come
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151350:29"/> by the like leaue granted to all Catholicks? Are religious companies, and Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, of ſo different nature, as that what is greatly good for the one, is naught for the other? Neither doth it ſatisfye, which Suarez ſayth n. 6. cit. <hi>That ſuperiors of regular orders are bound, not onely to procure the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, but allſo the perfection of their ſubiects:</hi> as if Bishops, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and ſuch as haue charge of ſonls, were not bound to procure the perfection of their ſubjects, and theſe allſo bound to be perfect? Did not our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſay indifferently to all: Matth. 5. <hi>Be perfect, as your heauenly father is perfect?</hi> Was not S. Iohn Baptiſt ſent. Luc. 1. <note place="margin">1. Ioan. 2. Qui, ſeruat verbumeius, in hoc ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas Deiper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect a eſt. Et c. 4. si dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus inuice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, charitas Dei in nobis perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta eſt.</note> 
                  <hi>to prepare a perfect people to our Lord,</hi> and yet was not ſent one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make Regulars? Doth not
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151350:30"/> God giue Paſtors and Doctors <hi>for conſummation</hi> (that is, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection) <hi>of Saints.</hi> Epheſ. 4? Or doth he giue none to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure perfection of Saints, but religious men? or were there no procurers of perfection in the Church, before religious orders were inſtituted? Or will religious Confeſſors ſay, that they are not to procure perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in their ſecular Penitents? Doth not Sotus lib. 10. de lure &amp; Iuſtitia q. 1. art 4. ſay. <hi>This is The duty of a Bishop, both to teach perfection, and perſwade it:</hi> and q. 3. art. 2. <hi>(It is the office of a Paſtor, to bring his healthfull flock to perfection:</hi> and noteth, that in the conſecration of a Bys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop, the Church telleth him, <note place="margin">Vt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibeat omnem homine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum.</note> that <hi>he must bring his flock to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as we read of S. Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:151350:30"/>
               <p>If any Regular should ſay to me, that (of it ſelf) it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for Catholicks, to confeſs to what approued Prieſt they would, then to thoſe who haue charge of ſouls, I would anſwer him, as <note n="†" place="margin">Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch. in Apop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theg.</note> Lycurgus anſwered one, who perſwaded to inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute popular gouerment in his citty, that he should firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginn ſuch a gouerment in his owne houſe. But whether they onely be to be accounted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, who obſerue the three Euangelicall Counſels, or no: I would know a reaſon, why it is requiſit, that ſuch as obſerue thoſe counſels, should confeſs to none, but to ſuch, as their regular Superiors appoint and the like should not be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for ſuch, as are to obſerue the commandements, as all Chriſtians are? Why should the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151350:31"/> obligation to confeſs to none; but to certain appointed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, be requiſit for obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of theſe Counſels, and the like obligation should not be requiſit for the obſeruation of the Precepts?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>ELEVENTH CHAPTER. That is better for a Penitent to confeſs to a Priest, who hath charge of his ſoule, then to an other, proued by the greater cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of abſolution.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe Eighth proof, that it is better for a Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to confeſs to a Prieſt, who hath charge of his ſoul, then to an other, I will take from the greater certainty of abſolution by him, then by this. Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151350:31"/> Curats, who haue char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of ſouls, haue iuriſdiction from the Canon law, and (as ſome <note n="a" place="margin">Sotus 4. di. 18. q. 4. art. 2.</note> graue diuines ſay) allſo from diuine law. Whereas Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors without charge of ſouls, haue Iuriſdiction onely by <note n="*" place="margin">S. Tho mas 2. 2. q. 188 ar. 4. q. 187. ar. 1. 4. S. Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura de pauper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate. Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min l. 2. de Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nachis c. 45.</note> delegation, except it be in the houre of death, when all Prieſts haue Iuriſdiction. And Iuriſdiction by law, eſpecially of God, is more certain, then is iuriſdiction by delegation, eſpecially when it muſt paſſe by ſo many hands of delegats and ſubdelegats, as it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly doth to ſuch Prieſts 'as vſually heare confeſſions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out charge of ſouls. And Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction being eſſentially requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit to abſolution, the more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the iu riſdiction is, the more certain is the abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:151350:32"/>2. Secondly, becauſe the Canon and Ciuil law ratifie and <note place="margin">L. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barius de of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris.</note> make good all acts done accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to law, by one who is commonly thought to be a lawfull ordinary officier, and hath any colourable title, though indeed he be no true officer, nor haue true iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Whereupon Sanchez lib. 3. de matrimonio Diſput. 22. n. 13. ſayeth. <hi>All things done by a Parish Prieſt, commonly taken to be ſuch, and hauing a colourable title giuen to him by a lawfull ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, are valid euen in court of conſcience, and confeſsions made to ſuch, need not be iterated.</hi> And Nauarre in Manuali c. 9. n. 11. <hi>In a Curate, a title, though naught, with poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſsion, will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi> But it is not certain, but denyed by many (as may be ſeen in Sanches l. cit. n. 15. and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151350:32"/> 6.) that acts done by a fals De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legate commonly thought to be a true delegate, are valid. Neither indeed is there the like reaſon, that the Law should ratifye the acts of ſuch, as are not inſtituted by Law, as there is, that it should ratifye the acts of ſuch, as law it ſelfe inſtituteth. So that, abſolution giuen by ones Curate, muſt needs be more certain, then giuen by an other, who is but delegate, becauſe the law it ſelf doth ratifye the abſolution giuen by a Curate, when of it ſelf it would not be valid, and doth not ratifye ſuch abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion giuen by a Delegate. And hence it is that (as we ſayd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) Diuines teach, that it is wiſer, euen at the houre of death when all Prieſts haue Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, to be abſolued of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151350:33"/> ones Curate or Superior, then of any other. And the validity of abſolution, being of that moment, that a Penitent ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing onely attrition, but valid abſolution, shall be ſaued, and wanting valid abſolution, shall be damned, well counſeled Reginald a Ieſuit l. 1. n. 103. <hi>Becauſe in a matter of ſuch impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, it behoueth to take the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and leaue the vncertain, Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez well aduiſeth, that vnleſs there be ſome great and reaſonable cauſe on the Confeſſors part, we should allwayes vſe the ſaifer meanes, that a Confeſſor hauing certain and more probable Iuriſdiction, be allwayes preferred before one, who hath a doubtfull or leſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable iuriſdiction.</hi> And (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs) a Curate, who hath charge of ſouls, hath more probable iuriſdiction, then a Delegate
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151350:33"/> who hath no ſuch charge. Which I doe not ſay, to call in queſtion the abſolution of ſuch Prieſts ſecular or Regular, who really haue trew Delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and for iuſt cauſe, of the ſea Apoſtolick, but becauſe ſuch Delegation paſſing tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough ſo many hands of Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gats and Subdelegats, as it commonly doth before it come to them, who vſually confeſs without charge of ſouls, is not ſo certain, to vs, as is the <note n="a" place="margin">See what Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus ſayd ſuprà cap. 10.</note> abſolution giuen to vs by Curats, who haue charge of ſouls. Nor are their Acts (if they be of themſelues inualid) ratifyed, and made good by Law, as are the Acts of Curats, though of themſelues they were inualid. I add allſo, that Curats doe ſucceed the 72. Diſciples as <note n="b" place="margin">Gloſſ. liu. 10. Sotus l. 10. de Iure q. 3. art. 1.</note> Diuines doe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151350:34"/> teach, and therefore are inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, not onely by men, but allſo by God, whereas Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gats <note place="margin">Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. l. 1. de Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricis c. 14. S. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas 3. q 6. a. 1.</note> are inſtituted onely by men, nor doe ſucceed the 72. Diſciples: and that, of the 72. Diſciples Chriſt ſayd Luc. 10. <hi>Who heareth you, heareth me.</hi> And it is more ſure to be abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of ſuch, as ſucceed them, of whom Chriſt ſayd, <hi>who hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth you, heareth me,</hi> then of others, of whom Chriſt ſayd no ſuch thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:151350:34"/>
               <head>TWELFTH CHAPTER. That it is better for a Penitent, to confeſs to a Prieſt, who hath charge of his ſoule, then to an other, becauſe it is more meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, and allſo more ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe ninth proof, that it is better for a Penitent, to confeſs to one who hath charge of his ſoul, then to an other, we will take from that it is both more meritorious, and alſo more ſatisfactorious. That it is more meritorious, I proue firſt, becauſe it is more merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to confeſs to ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, as God hath both inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, and commanded vs to confeſs vnto, and allſo the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151350:35"/> Church for many ages hath commanded, then to ſuch, as men haue inſtituted, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God, nor the Church euer commanded vs to confeſs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but we chuſe of our ſelues. For in the one, we fullfill God and the Churches will, and in theother, we fullfill our owne will. And ſurely, it is more me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious, to fullfill Gods and the Churches will, then to full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill our owne; becauſe there is more obedience to God and to the Church, and allſo more humility. But Curats, who haue charge of ſouls, are of the firſt ſorte, and who haue no charge of ſouls, are of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Secondly, I proue it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe commonly it is harder to confeſs to ones Curate, who hath charge of our ſouls, and authority to gouuernevs, then
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151350:35"/> to another, whome we chuſe our ſelues, and who hath no authority to gouerne vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ordinarily men are more loath to diſcouer their imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to their Superiors with whome they commonly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, then to others, who are not their Superiors, and who may be ſuch, as they neuer ſaw before, nor perhapps shall ſee afterwards. And where is the greater difficultye there is the greater vertue, and merit to ouercome. And hence allſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, why it is more ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious: for where there is <note place="margin">See Nauar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re de Indulg. notab. 3. n. 13.</note> greater paine or difficultye, there is allſo the greater ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thirdly I proue it to be more meritorious, becauſe in confeſſing to ſuch, as the Church apointeth and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151350:36"/> at leaſt once a yeare we conſerue the order and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of the Church, but in confeſſing to whom we chuſe our ſelues, we doe not keep that order or diſcipline. And how great a good it is, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the order and diſcipline of the Church, and what great harme may come by not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing it, we may ſee by the great account, which Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars make of their Regular or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and diſcipline, as we heard <note n="*" place="margin">Cap. 11.</note> before. And if they make ſuch account of their Regular diſcipline, and eſteeme it ſo great merit to obſerue it, how much more ought good chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Church to obſerue and eſteeme the diſcipline of the Church, she being incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably to be eſteemed aboue all regular orders, and her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151350:36"/> inſtituted by more ſure aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d allſo for more glorie of God and good of ſouls: wherefor if there be great merit in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing regular diſcipline, there is far more in obſeruing the Churches Eccleſiaſticall. diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline: and if greater harme come of breaking that, more cometh in breaking this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iuſt cauſe. Fourthly, I proue, that it is more merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to confeſs to ones Curate, who hath charge of his ſoul, then to an other, becauſe that conſerueth and increaſeth that ſpirituall and holy loue, which ought to be between a Paſtor and his sheep, whereof we shall ſpeak more hereafter, and all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo maintaineth his ſpirituall auctority, which he hath to gouerne them: whereas by lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151350:37"/> our Paſtor, and confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to whome we will, we dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish both his loue, and his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. But it is far more meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious to conſerue the Paſtors loue and authority, then any way to diminish it, as it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>THIRTEENTH CHAP. That it is better for a Penitent to confeſs to a Parish Prieſt, who hath charge of his ſoul, then to an other, becauſe great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, and no inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie cometh bythat, and many inconueniencies come by this.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THat all commodityes, which can be gotten by the Sacrament of pennance, may be had by confeſſing to a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151350:37"/> Prieſt who hath charge of ſouls, and no inconueniencie can come thereby, is euident, becauſe ſuch a Confeſſor is of Gods inſtitution, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per miniſter of that ſacrament. And all commodityes, which can be had by a ſacrament, may be had by the proper miniſter thereof inſtituted by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And likewiſe no inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencie can come by confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to ſuch an officer, as is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly appointed by God. But if there chance to fall out any inconueniencie, that riſeth of the perſon, not of the office it ſelf. But by confeſſing to others, whom we chuſe our ſelues, there may riſe many and great inconueniencies. Firſt, is preiudice of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, <note place="margin">Firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie,</note> who hath charg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of our ſouls, for it is his right to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151350:38"/> this ſacrament to all thoſe, of whoſe ſouls he hath charge. And not to giue to one his right or due, is doubtleſs a preiudice to him. Nether lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it to be a preiudice to him, becauſe leaue is granted to doe it, for that will not shew, that it is not a true preiudice to him, but onely that ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice is done with leaue. And Nouarre in <hi>C. Placuit</hi> n. 61. both affirmeth and proueth, that it is true preiudice to Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, that their people are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to confeſs to others: and it is euident, becauſe all taking away of ones right is a preiudice to him, though if it be done for iuſt cauſe, it be no ſinn. And how carefull the Church was in ancient times, to conſerue the rights of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaries, the Catechiſme
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151350:38"/> ad Parochos c. de Paenitent. <note place="margin">The Church here to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt carefull of the right of ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> ſect. 47. shweth in theſe words: <hi>with what religion in times paſt, in the moſt ancient Church, the right of an ordinary Prieſt was conſerued, is eaſily gathered by the ancient Decrees of Fathers, by which was ordained, that no Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop nor Prieſt should dare to doe any thing in an others Parish, without his leaue, who there go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned, or without ſome great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. An other inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie <note place="margin">Second incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> is, that libertie to confeſs to what approued Prieſt one will, breaketh diſcipline of the Church which is, that euery one should co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſs, at leaſt once a yeare, to his proper Prieſt, as is euident by the foreſayd Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the great Councel of Lateran. And a third inconue <note place="margin">Third Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> niencie is, that it leſſeneth that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151350:39"/> ſpirituall loue, which ought to be between a Paſtor and his sheep, whereof we shall ſpeake <note place="margin">Fourth Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> more hereafter. And a fourth is, that it leſſeneth the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which a Paſtor should haue ouer his flock, which doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs would be greater, if his sheep did confeſs to him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe naturally men reſpect and reuerence them more, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they confeſs their ſinns, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they doe not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs. And this noteth P. Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t 4. Can. <hi>Etſi animarum,</hi> ſaying, that voluntarie confeſſors <hi>breed contempt and indeuotion against proper Prieſts.</hi> I diſpute not, whether this Bull of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent the 4. be reuoked, or no, becauſe I argue not out of the obligation thereof, but out of the truth it ſayeth, which is, that voluntarie Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151350:39"/> occaſion neglect of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Prieſts, which ſo graue and ſo learned a Pope, as Innocent 4. was, would not haue ſayd, if he had not ſeen it to be tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And how great an inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencie neglect of Paſtors is, is manifeſt of it ſelf, ſeing all communities ſtand by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of their ſuperior, and fall and are weakened, by the fall or weakening of it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5. 1. Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal. 5. Heb. 15 Matth. 26. S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian Epiſt. 55 65. S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. contra Lucifer.</note> the Apoſtle often and earneſtly exhorteth Chriſtians to honnour and reuerence their ſpirituall ſuperiors, and our Sauiour ſayeth, <hi>if the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor be ſtrucken theep are diſperſed,</hi> and holy Fathers note, that the neglect of Paſtors, is the roote of ſchiſme and hereſie, and that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tye of the Church, dependeth on the honnor of Paſtors. And Layman, cited
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:151350:40"/>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Sup. c. 9.</note> before noteth, that by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing to whome one will, <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pretending impediments of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, withdraw themſelves from the Iuriſdiction of their Paſtor.</hi> A fifth inconueniencie by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie <note place="margin">Fifth Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> of confeſſing to what Prieſt one will, is, that one may omitt annuall confeſſion, and ſay, that he hath confeſſed, when he hath not confeſſed att all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſixth inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie <note place="margin">Sixt Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> is, that by libertie of chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ones Confeſſor, occaſion is taken to committ or conti new in ſinn, which would be much reſtrained, if men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to their proper Prieſts. For by this libertye, (as P. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent 4. in the Foreſayd Bull noteth) <hi>thereby shame, which is a great part of pennance, is taken away, whiles ones confeſſeth his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151350:40"/> ſinnes not to his proper Priest, whome he hath continuall and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but to an other, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to one, who is a paſſenger, to whome there is hard recourſe, and ſometimes impoſsible.</hi> And Azor. tom. 1. l. 5. c 25. granteth, that <hi>leaue to chuſe a Confeſſour, who may abſolue him from ſinns to be committed, doth giue occaſion to ſinn more freely, and more eaſily.</hi> And what great difference is <note place="margin">See Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is An. 1246. p. 634.</note> there (for this purpoſe) bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ween leaue to chuſe a Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, who may abſolue one from ſinns to be committed, and leaue to chuſe a Confeſſor, who may abſolue from ſinns that are committed? what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference (I ſay) is there for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitye to ſinn, between leaue to chuſe a Confeſſor, who may abſolue one from ſinns to be committed, and leaue to chuſe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151350:41"/> a Confeſſor, who may abſolue one from ſinns that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, which leaue all haue who haue libertie to confeſs to what Prieſt they will. For faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litye to ſinn, riſeth not preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of leaue to chuſe a Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, which may abſolue one from ſinns to be committed, but from leaue to a chuſe a Confeſſor, who may abſolue from ſinns, whether they be committed, or to be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A ſeuenth inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie <note place="margin">The Seue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th.</note> in leauing ones proper Prieſt, and conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſing to others, is, that thereby he is made leſs able to help ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, and cure the ſpirituall diſeaſes of his sheep. For by confeſſing to him, he should better know the State of the ſouls of his sheep, and to be
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151350:41"/> better able to apply proper re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medyes to them, to better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct their ignorance, and all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo better encourage them to follow vertue, and auoid ſuch vices, as they are ſubiect vnto. But of this we haue ſpoken ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mething, and shall more here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. An eight inconueniency <note place="margin">Eight Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> is, that by leauing our Paſtor and confeſſing to others, we diſcourage him, and make him leſs carefull of doing his deutye or what good he can doe for vs. For he, ſeing his sheep to leaue him, and goe to others, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring them before him, hath not that courage to labour for them, as he would haue, if he ſaw them preferre him before others. And what harme co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by the negligence of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, God himſelf declareth Ezechiel. 54. ſaying: <hi>my sheep
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151350:42"/> are diſperſed, becauſe there was no Paſtor.</hi> Not becauſe there was no Paſtor at all, but becauſe there was no diligent Paſtor. And Sotus lib. 10. de Iure &amp; Iuſtit. q. 3. art. 4. affirmeth, that the roote of hereſies in Germanye and England, was the negligence of Paſtors: and ſurely the sheeps neglect of their Paſtors, occaſioneth the Paſtors neglect of them. And if the negligence of Paſtors be the occaſion of ſuch ill, how much more is the want of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors? Whereupon the ſame So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in the ſayd place ſayeth: <hi>It is a diuine commandement, that euery Dioceſe haue a Bishop, for the peculiar care and watchfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which is due vnto it.</hi> And Bellarmin. lib. 1. de Pontif. c. 2. hauing cited theſe words of Caluin: <hi>They conuince, that to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151350:42"/> euerye Church ought a Bishop to be giuen,</hi> anſwereth. <hi>If by theſe examples, taken from moſt graue Fathers, we conuince, that to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye Church ought to be giuen a Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop, why doth not he ſuffer Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops?</hi> which is plainly to affirme, that examples brought by moſt graue Fathers, conuince, that euerye Church ought to haue a Byshop. And it is ſayd in his life l. 3 c. 5. that he counſeled P. Clement 8. to prouide Bys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops preſently for vacant Churches, leaſt he should be guiltye of ſouls perishing for want of Paſtors. And it is me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable what S. Bede l. 3. hiſt. Anglic. c. 7. Writeth of Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walch King of the Weſt Saxons in England, who hauing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled his Byshop, ſuſtained great loſſes and ſpoyles in his kingdome of his ennemies; <hi>He
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:151350:43"/> vnderſtood, that by want of Bys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops, he wanted allſo the help and grace of allmightye God: wherefore he ſent Embaſſadors into France to Agilbert, beſeeching him that he would returne and reſume againe his Bishoprick, affirming withall, to make ſatisfaction for that which was paſt.</hi> Thus S. Bede. And if ſo many, and ſo great incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniencies follow Penitents not confeſſing to their proper Prieſts, who haue charge of their ſouls, there was ſome great neceſſitye, which forced the Church to diſpenſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as no doubt that was, which before we rehearſed out of S. Thomas and others, to witt, too great number of penitents for to confeſs to one onely Prieſt, and too great want of ſufficient proper Prieſts gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally for all parts. And good
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151350:43"/> children of the Church, will rather doe what the Church of her ſelf commandeth, then what vpon neceſſity she diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth withall, and onely permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. But out of all which I haue ſayd in this chapter, I argue thus: It is of it ſelf farr better to auoid ſo many and ſo great inconueniencies, as haue been rehearſed, then to fall into them: but Penitents by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing to ſuch Prieſts as haue charge of their ſouls doe auoid the ſayd inconueniencies, and by confeſſing to others, doe fall into them. Therefor it is far better to confeſs to thoſe kindes of Prieſts, then to theſe. And what good Penitent will not doe that, which of it ſelf is far better?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:151350:44"/>
               <head>FOVRTEENTH CHAPT. That of it ſelf it is better for a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, to confeſs to his proper Prieſt, then to others, becauſe naturally he loueth his penitents more then others doe.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THat of it ſelf, it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">Paſtors loue their peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents more, then other Prieſts do.</note> for Penitents to confeſs to their proper Prieſts, who haue charge of their ſouls, then to others, I proue by the greater loue, which proper Prieſts who haue charge of their Penitents ſouls, natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue more, then other Prieſts haue, who haue no ſuch charge of the ſouls of their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents, becauſe his greater loue will make him more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and diligent to doe his Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151350:44"/> all the good he can, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then an other, who leſs loueth them. For the greater loue will cauſe the greater care. And that a Paſtor or proper Prieſt, who hath charge of his Penitents ſouls, naturally lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them more then others, who haue no ſuch charge, is euident, becauſe he accounteth his penitents his owne sheep, and naturally one loueth what it his own, more then an other, who accounteth it not his own. Whereupon well wrote Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. lib. 1. de Pontif. c. 3. <hi>It is certain, that Princes will take more care of their own, then Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars will doe of that which is other mens.</hi> And our Sauiour Ioan. 10. <hi>A good pastor giueth his life for his sheep,</hi> as if it were the property of a good Paſtor, to loue his sheep ſo much, as for
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:151350:45"/> loue of them, to giue his life for them. And as himſelf ſayth Ioan. 15. the greateſt ſigne of loue, is, to giue his life for one. See more of this in S. Chyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome lib. 2. de Sacerdotio c. 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, becauſe the Penitents of a Paſtor or proper Prieſt, are ſpecially committed to him by God. And ſurely, who loueth God, will ſpecially loue them, who are ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him by God, more then others will, to whome God hath not eſpecially com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them. For Gods ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall charge, will make him who loueth God, to haue a more ſpeciall care of them, then others, who haue no ſuch ſpeciall charge. As we ſee all honeſt men haue à more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care of children commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them by their parents,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151350:45"/> then others haue, to whome ſuch children were neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. And hereupon our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſayd, Ioan. 20. to S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: <hi>Doest thou loue me, more then theiſe? Feed my sheep:</hi> the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby shewing, that naturally Paſtors loue more Chriſts sheep, then others doe. And likewiſe the Councel of Trent. ſeſl. 13. c. 1. ſayth to Bishops who are the cheif Paſtors: <hi>lett them remember, that they are Pastors, and that they ought ſo to gouerne their ſubiects, as they loue them like children and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> And Cardinall Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min <note place="margin">In vita Bellarm l. 3. c. 2.</note> wrote thus to a Byshop, who deſired to giue ouer his Bishoprick, to become reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious: <hi>who loued vs, and gaue his life for vs, vouchſafed to ſay to Peter, and in him vnto all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors: if thou louest me, feed my
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151350:46"/> sheep. Is there any, that dare ſay</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble words of Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin.</note> 
                  <hi>to our Lord, I will not feed thy sheep, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ast I leeſe my ſoul, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs there be ſome, who loue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lues, and not God? A true louer of God ſayth with the Apostle, I had rather be anathema from Chriſt for my brethren, then not vndertake that burden, which the loue of God hath impoſed vpon me. Albeit there can be no danger of ſaluation, where charitye reigneth.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">No da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion where charity rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gneth.</note> Behold. in S. Paul, the excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding loue of a good Paſtor to his sheep: behold allſo, how there is no danger in taking charge of ſouls, ſo it be done for loue of God. Nay ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the greater the charge of ſouls is, the greater is the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as Bozius sheweth, that there are more Popes, Saints, then anye Archbyshops or Byshops of one Epiſcopall ſea
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151350:46"/> in the world; and more Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byshops, Saints, then Byshops of any one Sea in his prouince, and more Byshops Saints, then Curats of any one Parish in his Dioceſe. And allbeit charge of ſouls be of it ſelf more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, then not charge, is, yet taken with the greater grace, and greater aſſiſtance of God, which he allwayes affordeth greater to them, to whome he giueth greater charge, it is not more dangerous, and it is farr more meritorious. And whatS. Chryſoſtom. ſayeth: <hi>It is a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruel, if any Rector be ſaued,</hi> he ſpeaketh (as Eſtius Hebr. 13. v. 17. well noteth) <hi>of ſuch, as vpon ambition onely, putt themſelues into that function, as is euident by the words following, becauſe for one lawfully called, and faithfully exerciſing that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:151350:47"/> as Chryſostom himſelf did, there is no danger.</hi> And what S. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome <note place="margin">Some Saints h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue refuſed to be Prieſts, as well as to be Paſtors</note> ſayth of Rectors, may be ſayd of ſimple Prieſts or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, if theiſe take ſuch courſes of life for wrong ends. And if ſome Saints haue refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be Byshops, more haue accepted it: and ſome allſo haue refuſed to be ſimple Prieſts, not for the danger, but for humilitye, becauſe they thought not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues worthy of ſuch a function. Zacheus, vpon confidence of Chriſts loue, accepted his offer to come to his houſe, and the Centurion, vpon humilitye, refuſed it: both well, but he better. So it be God, who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth charge of ſouls vpon vs, and we accept it for his loue, it cannot but be more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to him, to accept it, then
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:151350:47"/> to refuſe it, and leſs dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to vs, becauſe God, in his goodneſs bindeth himſelf to aſſiſt vs far more, in accepting for his loue, the burden which he impoſeth vpon vs then in refuſing it, when he impoſeth it: and leſs danger is, when God far more aſſiſteth vs. And hence ſome write, and gather it out of the Apocalypſe c. 2. and 3. that God giueth to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Byshop, a ſpeciall Angel Gardian.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly I proue, that a Paſtor or Proper Prieſt with charge of ſouls, loueth more his Penitents, then an other, who hath not ſuch charge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Paſtor is like to a Father to his sheep, and an other, is but like a Paedagog. For as the Apoſtle ſayeth to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians 1. Corinth. 4. <hi>Though yee
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151350:48"/> haue ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y thouſand Paedagogs, yet yee haue not manye Fathers, for I haue begotten yee in Chriſt by the gboſpel.</hi> And Paſtors, are the proper Fathers of their Paris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hioners, becauſe they begett them in Chriſt by baptiſme, and giue them their firſt ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life. And the loue of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is naturally greater, then is the loue of anye Paedagog. Sotus allſo lib 10. de Iure &amp; lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia q. 3. art. 1. ſayeth: <hi>The mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenarie flyeth, becauſe he is a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenarie, to whome the sheep are not proper, becauſe the sheep belong not to him, for as Chriſt ſayeth, they are not his own, as not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to him by Christ, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that he loueth them not, to witt, with that loue, which was demanded of Peter, whether he loued him more then the reſt.</hi> In <note place="margin">What is commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all is neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of all. Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle.</note> which words he sheweth,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151350:48"/> why the Penitents are the Paſtors own, and proper to him, to witt, becauſe they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to him by Chriſt, and that therefor there is a ſpeciall loue in a good Paſtor towards his sheep, as there was in S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which is not in others, to whome Chriſt hath not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his sheep, and he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: <hi>How can they loue ſouls to the loſs of their liues, whome they account not their owne?</hi> And the reaſon why God infuſeth a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall loue into a Paſtour, is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Paſtour muſt haue a ſpeciall care ouer ſuch, as God committeth to his charge, more then others need to haue, which ſpeciall care he cannot performe without a ſpeciall loue: and therefore as God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to Paſtors a ſpeciall care of his sheep, ſo he giueth them
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151350:49"/> a ſpeciall loue of his sheep: which ſpeciall loue he giueth not vſually to others to whome he giueth no ſpeciall care of his sheep. For as God and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doe not faile in things that are neceſſarie, ſo nether doe they abound in things that are ſuperfluous.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, I proue that a good Paſtor or proper Prieſt loueth more his Penitents, then an other Prieſt doth, becauſe for the loue of God, and of them, he bindeth himſelf to aſſiſt them in what danger ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and for their ſakes vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taketh the greateſt burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, which is to anſwer ſoul for ſoule for euerye one of them. And therefor not onely doeth to them all the good, which others doe, but hindeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf thereto, which others doe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151350:49"/> not, and (as <note n="†" place="margin">Lib. de Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudin.</note> S. Anſelme ſayth of them, who not onely doe good, but allſo vow to doe it) giueth not onely the fruit, but alſo the tree. Whereas other Confeſſors, nether binde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to aſſiſt their Penitents, nor will vndergoe that great burden of anſwering ſoul for ſoul For of Mendicants Rodri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quez tom. 1. q 35. art. 5. writeth, that they <hi>allwayes refuſed to put</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">See Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulas Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis parte 4. c. 2. §. 4. p. 119.</note> 
                  <hi>the heauye burden of Curats vpon their shoulders.</hi> And Bellarmin. lib. 2. de Monachis c. 45. ſayeth: <hi>They doe not miniſter ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things, of due:</hi> but doe miniſter them to whom, when, and where they pleaſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all binding of themſelues thereto; and <hi>therefor cannot aske releef of iuſtice or due, but onely of charitye, as they miniſter ſpirituall things, not out of dutye, but onely
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:151350:50"/> of charityc:</hi> Thus he. If any ſay, that Paſtors or Curats take that bond and burden vpon them, for loue of their tithes or reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news; I anſwer, that good Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats or Paſtors of ſouls doe not, and I ſpeake of good Curats, or ſuch good Confeſſors as haue charge of ſouls, and I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with ſuch good Confeſſors, as haue no charge of ſouls. Secondly, as it were againſt charitye to thinck, that ſuch as heare confeſſions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out charge of ſouls, doe it wholly or principally for loue of almes or reward: ſo it were againſt charitye, to thinck the like of good Curats. Thirdly, none in England, who may haue charge of ſouls, could vndertake that burden for loue of tithes or reuenew, becauſe there he can expect none. And
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151350:50"/> out of all which hath been ſayd and proued in this Chapter, it will eaſily appeare, that if anye Catholicks in England be not willing to haue ſuch Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors as loue them more, and binde themſelues to farr more for their loue, then others doe, they are not ſo deſirous of their own good, and aſſuredneſs to be holpen in what need ſoeuer, as in wiſedome and in loue to themſelues they ough to be, and as they would be, if it were in matter of their tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſtate, or temporal life. For who would not haue a good corporal Phyſitian, or Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, who would binde himſelf to aſſiſt him? And if anye should not loue more ſuch a Confeſſor, as loueth him farr more, then an other, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaketh the greateſt bond of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151350:51"/> loue that can be in this world, he should shew himſelf to be very vngratefull, and would be ashamed to doe the like to anye kinde of freind, in anye other matter whatſoeuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>FIFTEENTH CHAPTER. That it is better to confeſs to ones proper Prieſt, then to an other, becauſe he is a more noble officer or minister of the Sacrament of Pennance.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe twelft proof, that of it ſelf it is better to confeſs to ones proper Prieſt, who hath charge of their ſouls, then to others, I take from the greater excellencie of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and this I proue: firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Confeſſors with charge of ſouls were immediatly inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by Chriſt Ioan. 20. where
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151350:51"/> he ſayth to his Apoſtles, <hi>Take the holy Ghoſt, whoſe ſinns you shall remitt, they shall be remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:</hi> which power with charge of ſouls, doth remaine in Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops their ſucceſſors. For as S. Thomas ſayth 3. parte q. 67. art. <note place="margin">Bishops proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtics.</note> 2. <hi>Bishops ſucceed to the Apoſtles.</hi> Sotus 4. d. 21. q. 1. art. 4. <hi>By Gods law, Bishops ſucceed the Apostles,</hi> and the ſame he hath lib. 10. de Iure q. 1. art. 4. Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin. lib. 1. de Clericis c. 13. <hi>Bishops, properly ſucceed the Apostles.</hi> And cap. 14. <hi>All Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe conſtantly teach, that Bishops ſucceed the Apoſtles.</hi> And lib. 2. de Confirmatione c. 22. <hi>Bishops doe ſimply and abſoluty ſucceed the Apoſtles.</hi> The ſame ſayth Stapleton controu. 6. q. 3. art. 3. Nether doth anye Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick deny, that Bishops ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the Apoſtles in their
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151350:52"/> power and authoritye of forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſinns, by Chriſts own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. But the difficultye may be of other inferior Prieſts, who, vnder Bishops, haue charge of ſouls, as Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats haue, whether the office of ſuch were immediatly inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by Chriſt, or no. But the office of Curats may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered two wayes, ether as an <note place="margin">Office of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered two wayes.</note> office ſeparately taken by it ſelf, or as a parte of Epiſcopall office and authoritye, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding that, which was extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie in the Apoſtles, and neceſſarye for the beginning or founding of Chriſts Church, as the ſpirit of the 70. Seniors was but a parte of the ſpirit of Moyſes. And if the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice or authoritye of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats be thus conſidered, it is immediatly of diuine inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151350:52"/> as Epiſcopall authoritye is, and as the ſpirit of the 70. Seniors was. For it is of the ſame nature, of which Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall authoritye, though not ſo great, as Epiſcopall authoritye is: as Epiſcopall authoritye is of the ſame nature of which Apoſtolicall authoritye was, though not ſo high, and as the authoritye of the 70. Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ors was of the ſame nature with the authoritye of Moyſes. And if the office of Curats were but in this ſorte immediatly inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Chriſt, it would appeare to be farr nobler, then is theirs, who heare confeſſions without charge of ſouls. For the office of thoſe, was neuer inſtituted immediatly by Chriſt, either ſeparatly by it ſelf, or in a whole, whoſe parte thereof it is, but is of a different nature.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151350:53"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:151350:53"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:151350:54"/> becauſe Chriſt, neuer inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an office to forgiue ſinns without charge of ſouls.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But indeed it is more probable, that the office of Curats was it ſelf inſtituted im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly by Chriſt, or by the Apoſtles at his command. Firſt, becauſe (as Suarez confeſſeth tom 3. de relig. l. 1. c. 17. n. 25. <note place="margin">The office of Curats, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye to the Church</note> and it is euident) <hi>The inſtitution of Curats is neceſſarye to the good gouuerment of the Church, and ſaluation of ſouls.</hi> And Chriſt, either inſtituted, or comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be inſtituded, all, that is neceſſarye to the good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerment of the Church and ſaluation of ſouls. For Gods workes are perfect, and euen in naturall things, he giueth all that is neceſſarye to their well being. Secondly, becauſe Chriſt, beſides the Apoſtles,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151350:54"/> inſtituted 72. Diſciples Luc. 10. and gaue them authoritye to preach, as he did to the Apoſtles, and becauſe authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye to preach without authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to adminiſter neceſſarie ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments att leaſt, (as the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Pennance is) were imperfect, therefor ether him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf gaue or appointed his Apoſtles to giue them authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye to adminiſter that ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And as S. Thomas ſayeth 3. q. 67. art. 2. <hi>Chriſt gaue to the Apoſtles the office of baptizing, but to be exerciſed by others,</hi> and <note place="margin">Bishops and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and 72. Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</note> by whom rather, then by the 72. Diſciples? Beſides, Sotus lib. 10. de Iure q. 3. art. 1. ſayeth: Byshops and Parish Prieſts ſucced the Apoſtles and 72. Diſciples Can. in nouo d. 6. And Bellarmin. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> de Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricis c. 14. <hi>All Fathers conſtantly
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151350:55"/> teach, that Bishops ſucceed the Apoſtles, and Priests the 72. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</hi> And if any Prieſts ſucceed the 72. Diſciples, ſurely Parish Prieſts, ſuch as haue charge of ſouls. Thirdly, becauſe the Apoſtles Epheſ. 4. ſayth, that Chriſt gaue ſeparatly to his Church, <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets, Euangeliſts, Paſtors,</hi> where, by <hi>Pastors,</hi> he vnderſtandeth ſuch as are not Byshops, for Byshops he vnderſtandeth vnder the name of Apoſtles, to whome they ſucceed. And though ſome by <hi>Pastors</hi> vnderſtand <hi>Byshops,</hi> yett they include allſo ſuch Prieſts, as vnder Bishops, haue charge of ſouls, as is to be ſeen in Eſtius vpon that place. And the ſame Apoſtle, Acts 20. calling to him the presbyters or elders of the Church, of Epheſe ſayeth indifferently to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151350:55"/> them all, that <hi>the holye Ghost had putt them to gouerne the Church of God;</hi> where that by <hi>Presbyters,</hi> he includeth not onely Byshops, but allſo ſuch Prieſts, as haue care of ſouls, appeareth, both becauſe the word <hi>Presbyter,</hi> was in the Apoſtles time common to all ſuch, as is euident, and there is no conuincing reaſon to proue, that the Apoſtle there reſtrained the common vſe of that word, as allſo becauſe S. Thomas 2. 2. q. 184. art. 6. ſayeth, that S. Paul there <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendit vtroſque,</hi> and the ſame ſayth Bellarmin l. 1. de Pontif. c. 8. And Stapleton vpon that place: <hi>Paul here afſirmeth, that the Presbyters of Epheſus were made ouerſeers of God flock, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ofſice of ouerſeers belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth as much to a Parish Priest, as
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151350:56"/> to a Bishop of manye cittyes.</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reouer, here is ſayd, that there were manye Presbyters in the Church of Epheſus, and yett there neuer were manye <note n="*" place="margin">Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius in Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bio l. 6. S Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. in Socrate l. 6 c. 12</note> Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops in one Church. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here vnder that name, were allſo, included ſome Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, who were no Bishops. I add allſo. that S. Thomas 2. 2. q. 184. art. 6. expoundeth thoſe wordes, <hi>opitulationes &amp; guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationes</hi> 1. Corinth. 12. of Arch. deacons, and Curats, which Eſtius vpon that place, ſayth, is the common expoſition of the Latins. Fourthly l proue the immediate diuine inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch Prieſts, as haue charge of ſouls, out of the Councel of Trent. ſeſſ. 23. Can. 6. <hi>If anye shall ſay that in the church, there is not a Hierarchie inſtituted by Gods appointement,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:151350:56"/> which conſiſteth of Bishops, Prieſts, and miniſters, be he anathema.</hi> And Eſtius in 1. Corinth. 12. v. 27. ſayeth: <hi>The Eccleſiaſticall Hierarchie properly conſisteth of Bishops, Priests, and Deacons.</hi> And ſeeing <hi>Hierarchie</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth formally in power to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, or in Principalitye, as is euident by the word itſelf, the Councel muſt needs meane, that by Gods inſtitution, ſome Prieſts who are not Byshops, are gouernors in his Church. And if anye, ſurely ſuch as haue charge of ſouls. Fiftly I proue it out of the profeſſion of the Church in the conſecration of Prieſts, where thus she profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: <hi>when God had appointed Byshops to gouerne people, he choſe men of inferior order, and of ſecond degree, for to help their ſocietye and worke.</hi> And she addeth, that the like was done in the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151350:57"/> wilderneſs, by giuing 70. elders to Moyſes, and in the Synagog, by inſtituting Prieſts, and after that addeth allſo: <hi>By this proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to the Apostles of thy Sonne, thou haſt adioyned preachers of fayth, as companions, by whome they haue filled the world with hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pye preachings. Wherefore o Lord, we beſeech thee, add to our weakneſs theiſe helpers, who by how much we are the frayler, by ſo much the more we need them. Let them be prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cooperators of oure order, lett shine in them the forme of all iuſtice, that being to giue good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the diſpenſation commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them, they may obtain the reward of euerlaſting happineſs.</hi> In which words, the Church profeſſeth, that ſuch Prieſts, as are to giue account of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation committed to them (as thoſe are, who haue charge of ſoules) are by Gods inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151350:57"/> cooperators of Byshops, as the 70. elders were to Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and Prieſts in the Synagog, were to the high Prieſt. I add allſo, that the iuriſdiction of Byshops and of Prieſts, is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent iure druino. For thus Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin. lib. 1. de Clericis c. 14. <hi>The Catholick Church acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth and teacheth, that Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye is greater iure diuino, then Priest hood, both in order and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction,</hi> which ſuppoſeth, that Prieſtly iuriſdiction, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted iure diuino, and in whome, if not in Curats? And the ſame Bellarmin. praefat. lib. de Clericis ſayeth: <hi>The Church is diſtinguished by Chriſt, into three orders,</hi> among which he putteth Curats. So that Curats are by Chriſts order in the Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Secondly, I proue, that <note place="margin">Curats, of their prime inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter all prieſtly ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers not.</note>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:151350:58"/> a Curate is a more noble offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer and miniſter of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Pennance, then an other who hath not charge of ſouls; becauſe he is inſtituted not onely to miniſter the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Pennance, but allſo all other ſacraments which Prieſts can miniſter: whereas ſuch as haue no charge of ſouls, be inſtituted onely to miniſter the ſacrament of Pennance and the Euchariſt, as is to be ſeen in Catholick Countryes, and if they haue leaue to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter other Sacraments, that is onely in heathen and heretick countryes, and for want of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats. But he is a more noble mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the ſacrament of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, who of his prime inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, is to miniſter all ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which Prieſts can mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, then ſuch, as of their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151350:58"/> inſtitution, can miniſter onely two ſacraments.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Thirdly becauſe Curats, <note place="margin">Curats haue true iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ouer their flock. not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> and ſuch as haue charge of ſouls, haue not onely power and authoritye to miniſter ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, but allſo to rule and gouerne people, as Paſtors doe sheep, and therefor Curats are termed by S. Thomas (as we shall ſee hereafter) <hi>leſſer Princes, and inferior Prelats of the Church,</hi> ad are a parte of the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Hierarchie or Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and Bellarmin. l. 1. de Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tif. c. 8. ſayth: <hi>we grant, that it agreeth to Bishops and Priests, to feed and gouerne the Church.</hi> Whereas ſuch, as haue no charge of ſouls, haue no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritye to gouern them, but as they voluntarily miniſter ſacraments to them, ſo theiſe voluntarily receaue ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151350:59"/> of them, and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily doe what they aduiſe them. Wherefor there is no true obedience, or merit of obedience to them, becauſe they haue no true ſuperioritye or power to command. But in doing what Curats command, there is true obedience, and merit thereof, and likewiſe true diſobedience and demerit thereof in not doing what they command, becauſe they haue true ſuperioritye and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye to command their flock. And doubtleſs, he is a more noble miniſter of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Pennance, who hath <note place="margin">Curats are the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers but Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</note> not onely power to miniſter ſacraments, but allſo iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and power to rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne them, to whome he mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtreth the ſacrament of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, then he, who hath no
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151350:59"/> iuriſdiction and power to rule and gouerne them to whome he miniſtreth the ſacrament of pennance. I add allſo, that <note place="margin">See <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas 2. 2. q. 187 art. 1.</note> Curats haue authoritye in themſelues to miniſter ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but who haue no charge of ſouls, are but Delegats, and haue onely the vſe of authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, which is in an other. And allſo, that theiſe are but Coad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iutors <note place="margin">Rodri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 1. q 59. art. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. to 3. q. 31. art 4.</note> of the others. And a Coadiutor is inferior to the Principall.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Fourthly I proue that Curats are more noble officers and miniſters of ſacraments, by authorityes. For as the Gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Luc. 10. ſayth: <hi>Byshops are like to the Apoſtles; inferior Priests, to witt Curats, are like to the 72. Diſciples.</hi> And Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally the Fathers teach, that as Byshops ſucceed the Apoſtles,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:151350:60"/> ſo Prieſts who haue charge of ſouls, ſucceed the 72. Diſciples as Concil-Neoceſar. Can. 3. Damaſ. Epiſt. 3. Anaclet. Epiſt. 2. Auguſtin. in Pſalm. 44. Leo Epiſt. 83. Iſidorus lib. 2. de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin. offic. Beda in c. 10. Lucae. And S. Thomas 3. part. q. 67. art. 1. ſayeth: <hi>To baptize, belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Curats, leſſer Princes of the Church ſucceed the 72. Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</note> 
                  <hi>to leſſer Princes of the Church, that is, to Prieſts, who hold the place of the 72. Diſciples of Christ, as the Gloſſe ſayth Lucae</hi> 10. Sotus l. 9. de lure q. 4. art. 3. <hi>We muſt needs grant, that the office of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats hath the higheſt place of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall functions.</hi> And 4. d. 18. q. 1. art. 5. <hi>Curats of Parishes haue ordinarye power, not from Byshops but from Gods law.</hi> Ibid. q. 4. art. 2. <hi>All thoſe</hi> (Pope, Byshops, Curats,) <hi>are called ordinaries by Gods Law. For allbeit the Bys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop giueth a Parochiall Church to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151350:60"/> this or that man: yet whoſoeuer is Parish Priest, is by Gods Law the proper Priest, as allbeit the chuſing of the Pope, belongeth to Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls, and the chuſeing of Bishops, to Canons, yett they haue power from Gods Law. For Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who choſe the Apostles, to whom Byshops ſucceed Can. Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vices d. 68. choſe allſo 72. others helpers of them, to whome Prieſts ſucceed Can. In nouo d.</hi> 6. Azor. allſo tom. 1. l. 11. c. 24. ſpeaking of Curats, ſayeth: <hi>It cannot be denyed, that the ſtate of Bishops and Priests, was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Christ our Lord, as ſayth Anacletus, and it is related Can. in nouo d. 21. Byshops ſucceed to the Apostles, Priests to the 72. Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi> And Suarez tom. 3. dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. lib. 1. c. 17. n. 25. <hi>Gerſon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that the ſtate and office of Curats, is by Gods law, and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151350:61"/> Christs institution, ſo as the Pope cannot take it out of the Church, as he cannot take away the state of Byshops, becauſe Curats belong to the entire Hierarchicall order in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted by Christ. And this is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, both by most ancient tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and becauſe the inſtitution of proper Curats, is neceſſarie to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Curats neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſoules.</note> 
                  <hi>the good gouerment of the Church, and ſaluation of ſouls.</hi> And (as I ſayd before) doubtleſs, Chriſt inſtituted all that is neceſſarye to the good gouerment of the Church and ſaluation of ſouls. Nether will it follow, that Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats are of mans inſtitution, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſometime Vicars are putt in their place; for though Gods affirmatiue lawes doe binde all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, yet not for allwayes: and allſo, becauſe Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Vicars, and Archprieſts, are ſometimes put in places of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:151350:61"/> Byshops, and yet none deny, that Byshops are of Chriſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. Beſides, Vicars, who are putt in place of Curats, haue charge of ſouls, which is all one for my purpoſe. Finally, S. Thomas 3. part. q. 67. art. 2. calleth Curats <hi>leſſer Princes of the Church.</hi> And 22. q 188. art. 4. <hi>ordinarye. Prelats of the Church,</hi> and addeth, that <hi>for one to preach by authoritye of Prelats or to doe other ſuch things, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not the degree of a diſciple or ſubiect.</hi> Item. <hi>Religious, are instituted to preach and heare</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars ſerue Curats.</note> 
                  <hi>Confeſsions, not by their owne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritye, but by the authoritye of ſuperior and inferior Prelats, to whome that belongeth by office. And ſo they ſerue Prelats in ſuch miniſterie, which is proper to ſuch a Religion.</hi> And S. Bonauenture lib. de Paupertate Chriſti p.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151350:62"/> 422. <hi>Religious men heelp Curats, not as Lords, not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hauing charge of ſouls, but as ſeruants in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye.</hi> And ſurely, ſeruants, and ſuch as worke by authoritye of others, are leſs noble officers, then thoſe, whome they ſerue, and by whoſe auctoritye they worke.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And to all theſe authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes <note place="margin">12. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tij An. 1624.</note> I add, that lately the holye Congregation de propaganda fide hath decreed, that <hi>the end of Seminaries is more excellent,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The end of Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent therof Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions.</note> 
                  <hi>then the end of Religions becauſe there is no ſacrifice more gratefull to God, then the zeale of ſouls.</hi> Which decree they made, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing called before them all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious orders, and without op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of anye of them. And if the end of Seminaries be more excellent, ſurely allſo the end of Curats, fot whome
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:151350:62"/> principally, ſeminaries are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted. And allſo, that the Councel of Trent. ſeſſ. 24. c. 18. commanded, that all Byshops, who were able, should in their Dioceſes found a ſeminarye for to bring vp Prieſts, who should take the charge of ſouls, which sheweth. that in the iudgement both of the ſayd Congregation, and Councel, Prieſts, who haue charge of ſouls, are more excellent offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and more vſefull and needfull to the Church, then ſuch are, who haue no charge of ſouls. I may add allſo, that not onely <note n="*" place="margin">Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r cus quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib. 12. q. 28. Maior 4. d. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8. q. 7. Gerſon tract. de ſtatu perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis. The ſtate of Curats in it ſelf per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecter then Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> ſecular Diuines, but allſo regular diuines doe grant, that the ſtate of Curats is perfecter, then the ſtate of Religious. For thus Suarez to. 3. de Relig. l. 1. c. 21. n. 6. <hi>If the ſtate of religious and inferior Pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lats,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151350:63"/> be conſidered in themſelues, the state of Prelats is more perfect.</hi> And this (doubtleſs) meant S. Auſtin, when he wrote epiſt. 148. <hi>There is nothing more happie before God, then the office of a Bys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop, Prieſt, or Deacon, if it be exerciſed as our Lord comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</hi> And S. Chryſoſtom, when he noted, that our Sauiour, hauing asked S. Peter if he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him more then others, bad him not enter into Religion, but to feed his sheep. And the Apoſtle, Philippens 1. choſe rather to help ſouls, then to be in heauen with Chriſt, ſo much they eſteemed paſtorall care of ſouls.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:151350:63"/>
               <head>SIXTEENTH CHAPTER. That it is better to confeſs to a Prieſt, who hath charge of ſouls, then to one who hath not, becauſe he is neceſſarie to the good gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, not others.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THat Prieſts, who haue charge of ſouls, as Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, are neceſſarye, to the good gouerment of the Church, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident by what hath been ſayd before, that they are immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appointed by Chriſt, and by the profeſſion of the Church, that they are ſuch, as were the 70. elders in the wilderneſs, and as ſimple Prieſts were in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagog. Secondly becauſe as in an armye, naturall reaſon tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs, that not onely a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall is neceſſarie, but allſo Captains of troupes, and vnder
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151350:64"/> them, ſergea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and Corporalls, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand immediatly eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye particular ſoldier: ſo reaſon will teach vs, in the Church, which is like to an Armye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Pope, who is Generall a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Byshops, who are Captaines of ſeuerall Dioceſes, there should be vnder them, Curats, who in euerye parish should immediatly command and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne euery particular Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And the ſame we ſee in euerye kingdome, where beſides the King, and Lieutena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of shires, there are Conſtables, in euerye village. Thirdly, becauſe Prieſts who haue charge of ſouls, are of the Eccleſiaſticall Hierarchie and who are of the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Hierarchie are neceſſarie for the good gouerment of the Church. For God and nature, as they faile not in neceſſaryes,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151350:64"/> ſo they abound not in ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluityes. Fourthly, becauſe Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez (as we ſaw aboue in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapter) granteth, that <hi>Curats are neceſſarie to the good gouerment of the Church, and ſaluation of ſouls.</hi> Fiftly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Church in all ages, and in all places, where she could inſtitute Prieſts with charge of ſouls, did inſtitute them, and deuided Chriſtian people, into diſtinct parishes, and lately the Councel of Trent commanded it to be done ſeſſ. 21. c. 4. ſeſſ 24. c. 13. Therefor she iudgeth ſuch to be neceſſarie to her good gouerme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, otherwiſe she would not ſo generally, and ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually haue practiſed it, and all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo command it. Whereby we ſee, that if any will hinder or diſſwade the erectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Curats, or diuiſion of Catholicks into
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151350:65"/> Parishes, they doe againſt the generall, and continuall prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Church, and againſt her good gouerment, and the commandement of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Trent. But that ſuch Prieſts, as haue no charge of ſouls, are not neceſſary to the good gouerme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Church, is euident, becauſe ſuch haue no authoritie at all to gouern, becauſe ſuch were not inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt, becauſe the Church for manye ages, had no ſuch, nor euer commanded ſuch to be inſtituted or vſed. And ſith euerye one ſeeth, of what importance the good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerment of the Church is, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye one may thereby fee, of what greater importance it is to haue Prieſts with charge of ſouls, rather then to haue others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:151350:65"/>
               <head>SEAVENTEENTH CHAP. That it is better to confeſs, to a priest hauing charge of ſouls, then to an other, proued by the compariſon of the ſpeciall motiues to confeſs to others.</head>
               <p n="1">1. HItherto we haue ſpoken of the ſpirituall motiues to confels to Prieſts, who haue charge of the ſouls of their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents rather then to others, which (as we haue ſeen) are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry manye, and allſo weightye; now we will ſee the ſpirituall motiues, which may be preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that it is better to confeſs to others. And I will omitt all temporall motiues thereto, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are vnfitta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye to be mentioned, when there is queſtion or delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which kinde of Confeſſors
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151350:66"/> are the beſt for the glorie of God, and ſpirituall good of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents. The firſt ſpirituall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, <note place="margin">Firſt motiue.</note> to goe to what approued Confeſſor one will, may be, that ſuch libertie doth in manye Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents help to make entire co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions more then would be, if they did euer confeſs to him, who hath charge of their ſouls, by reaſon of their bashfulneſs, or ſome other human wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kneſs. True it is, that libertye to confeſs to what approued Confeſſor one will helpeth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye to make entire confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, more then reſtraint to one ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued <note place="margin">Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and amand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, of more impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, then Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Church; but doth it not hinder as many to haue true contrition, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute purpoſe to amend what they doe confeſs? And ſeing contritio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is far more neceſſarie, and a more principall parte of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:151350:66"/> the ſacrament of pennance, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Confeſſion is, (becauſe contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may ſaue one without Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, when a Prieſt cannot be had, but Confeſſion without contrition, will doe no good) if reſtraint to confeſs to ſuch as haue charge of our ſouls, help more to contritio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and reſolute purpoſe of amendment oflife, then libertye of confeſſing to what Prieſt one will, doth, it muſt needs be better, becauſe it more helpeth to the more prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall parte of the ſacrament, which is contrition, and allſo more to the end of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is forgiueneſs of ſinns, and amendment of life, and a true Penitent will more regard that, which more hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth him to the more neceſſarie part of the ſacrament of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which is contrition, and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:151350:67"/> allſo to the end of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is forgiueneſs of ſinns, and amendment of his life, then that, which helpeth him more to the leſs neceſſarie parte of this ſacrament, which is entire confeſſion of his ſinns.</p>
               <p n="2">2. An other motiue to leaue <note place="margin">Second motiue.</note> the Confeſſor, who hath charge of ſouls, and to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſs to others, may be, that thereby the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Pennance, is more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherwiſe it would be: but notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding this, we should rather ſeeke, what hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth to receiue this ſacrament better, then what helpeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it oftner. Becauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it better, though ſeldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, profiteth much, whereas to receiue it oftener, but not better, profiteth little. And (as we haue shewed) confeſſing to ones proper Prieſt, who hath
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151350:67"/> charge of ſouls, helpeth much to confeſs better, then liberty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to confeſs to what Prieſt one will, doth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A third motiue may be, that <note place="margin">Third motiue.</note> diuers ſorts of Confeſſors, who haue not charge of the ſouls of their Penitents, can commonly giue greater Indulgences, then ſuch as haue charge of ſouls, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giue. To this I anſwer, that this motiue hath little place in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, where all Prieſts can giue ſufficient Indulgence. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that (as Bellarmin lib. 1. de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. cap. 11. well monisheth, after S. Thomas) <hi>Regular diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline muſt not be broken or relaxed for gayning of Indulgences.</hi> And if not regular diſcipline, much leſs Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline, which is of more importance, then regular diſcipline, as the Church is of more importance,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:151350:68"/> then anye regular order. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſith abſolution from ſinn, is of farr greater impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Indulgence, becauſe, that is, forgiueneſs of the ſinn it ſelf, this, but a relaxation from ſome te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall payne, after ſinn is abſolued, we should rather looke, what Prieſt can giue vs the moſt aſſured abſolution fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinn, then who can giue vs the greateſt Indulgence, which will auaile vs nothing, if our ſinn be not aſſuredly abſolued. Beſides, by confeſſing to one appointed to vs by the Church, we both merit and ſatisfye mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, then by confeſſing to one choſen by our ſelues (as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore shewed) and thereby more encreaſe grace in our ſouls, and our glorie in heauen, which is more to be eſteemed, then rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xatio of temporall payne. And
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:151350:68"/> Sotus 4. d. 21. q. 2. a. 1. ſayeth. <note place="margin">Incre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as of merit, better far then Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</note> 
                  <hi>of it ſelf, it is much better to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye by his own works, then to gain Indulgences.</hi> And ibid. <hi>Incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably better, is the least increaſe of merit and grace, then to be freed from the greateſt paine in Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Incomparably I ſay better to be with greater merit and grace in Purgatorie twenty yeares, then</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble words of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</note> 
                  <hi>with leſs, to be there but one day, yea to flye to heauen without all Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie.</hi> Which words are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be conſidered. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the valor or effect of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencet is not certain, vnleſs the cauſes of granting them be <note n="*" place="margin">Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uar. de Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. notab. 15 So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus 4. d. 21. q. 2. art. 2. Bellar. min l. 1. de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg. c. 12.</note> iuſt and proportionable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Pope, is not Lord of the treaſure of the Church, but onely diſpenſor thereof, and which is a iuſt and proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable cauſe, <hi>onely God</hi> (as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uar. ſayth tract. de Indulg. no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tab.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:151350:69"/> 15. n. 8.) <hi>knoweth.</hi> And he addeth ibidem n. 17. <hi>That too large Indulgences giue occaſion to people to thinck, that more is got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by them, then is gotten indeed, and cauſeth more neglect of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, then ought to be.</hi> And num. 18. <hi>That the Pope may erre, in thinking this or that cauſe to be iust.</hi> And notab. II. n. 23. <hi>That it is moſt profitable, and most faif, to enioyne and accept pennance to be done in this life, and that it is not the part of a frind to enioyne ſmall pennances.</hi> And notab. 5. n. 44. <note place="margin">Setus 4. d. 20. q. 1. ar. 3 Paenite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae quae modo in vſu ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, non tam paeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poenite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiarum ludibria ſunt.</note> 
                  <hi>It is imperfection to ſeek Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, for after them to ſerue Christ coldly, and to vſe leſs wari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and remedie to auoid ſinns, and to roote out vices, which I feare this our age doth too much.</hi> And notab. 21. n. 2. approueth the opinion of Caietan, who ſayth, that who will gett In dulgences,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:151350:69"/> muſt haue a minde to doe as <note place="margin">See Nauar. notab. 9. n. 12. Sotus 4. d. 21. q. 2. art. 2.</note> great pennance himſelf, as would ſuffice for to ſatisfie for his ſinns. And this, ſaieth <note n="†" place="margin">l. 1. de Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. c. 13.</note> Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin is profitable and pious. <hi>by which</hi> (ſayth Nauar.) <hi>the hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Indulgences is conſerued, the mouth of raylers against them ſtopped, and Christians ſtirred vp to doe worthye fruicts of pennance.</hi> And notab. 31. n. 44. <hi>According</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">For In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces We muſt not for beare to doe acts of Penna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> 
                  <hi>to the opinion of Diuines and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts, we muſt not for Indutge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, forbeare to doe acts of Pennance.</hi> And finally notabl. 17. he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <hi>that it is too true, which the Gloſſe ſayth, That few gett Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces.</hi> Thus this pious, and moſt learned Canoniſt, which I wish them to conſider well, who for to gett greater Indulgences, would leaue their proper Prieſt, and confeſo to others. I add allſo, that Regular ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, <note place="margin">Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, for no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, will permitt theirs 10 con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to others.</note>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:151350:70"/> nether for more making of entire confeſſions, non ofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner frequenting the ſacrament of pennance, nor for gaining of greater Indulgences, nor for anye other motiue whatſoeuer, will permitt their ſubiects, out of caſe of neceſſitye, to confeſs to others, then to ſuch as they appoint. Which clearly she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that they eſteem more confeſſion made to proper Prieſts, then all other ſpirituall commodities, which can come by confeſſing to others. And <note place="margin">Onely neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Church</note> moreouer I adde, that no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter good, but onely the too great multitude of penitents, and the inſufficiencye of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Prieſts in diuers places, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Church to condeſcend to people for to leaue their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Prieſts, and to confeſs to others, as euident by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:151350:70"/> of S. Thomas, and others <note n="*" place="margin">Supra cap. 5.</note> before cited. And if not greater ſpirituall good, but onely neceſſitie by reaſon of too great multitude of Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, or inſufficiencye of ſome proper Priefts, moued the Church to grant libertie to Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to other Prieſts, good chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Church, who will follow her aduiſe, should not vpon pretenſe of greater ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall good, but onely vpon the ſayd neceſſitye, make vſe of that libertie, which she vpon that neceſſitye, was forced to grant, and if that neceſſitye had not been, would neuer haue granted. I ſay allſo that it is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine precept, <hi>doe fruits worthye of pennance</hi> Luke 3. And to doe fruits worthye of pennance, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth (as <note n="*" place="margin">l. 4. de poenit. c. i.</note> Bellarmin <note n="†" place="margin">See Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. 20. in Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. S. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas in Luc. 3.</note> well ſayth and proueth out of holye
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:151350:71"/> Fathers) to make ſatisfaction to God, and as he affirmeth: <hi>They cannot be well called fruits worthye of pennance, vnleſs indeed they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to recompenſe the iniurye, if not inequalitye of qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titye, yet in equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litye of proportion, and according to the acceptance of him, who was wronged:</hi> And alſo that Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces doe not exempt vs from fullfilling this diuine precept. And likewiſe, that not Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, <note place="margin">Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences are not ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, nor exempt from doing fruits of penna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</note> but the Penitents ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, is a part of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Pennance, without which <hi>the ſacrament of Pennance</hi> (as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me Bellarmin <note n="†" place="margin">Lib. 1. de Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent. c. 17. See him ib. l. 4. c. 8.</note> ſayth) <hi>is lame and imperfect,</hi> which lameneſs or imperfection, Indulgences doe not ſupplie, becauſe they are no parte att all of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Nether is it likelye, that Chriſt, in granting Indulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces to his Church, meant thereby
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:151350:71"/> to make his ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lame and imperfect, or to exempt peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents from full filling his diuine precept, of doing worthye fruits of pennance, which (as Nauar. ſayd) is the doctrine of diuines and of Canoniſts. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſay with Bellarmin. l. 1. de Indulgentiis c. 12. <hi>That prudent Christians doe ſo take Indulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, as with all they endeauour to bring fruites worthie of pennance, and to ſatisfye God for their ſinnes.</hi> Which prudent aduiſe who wel conſider, wil not for vncertain gayning of greater Indulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, leeſs the certain gaining of greater merit in confeſſing to their proper Prieſt: eſpeciall, ſeeing merit (as truly ſayd So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus) is incomparably more to be eſteemed, then Indulgence, though the gaining of this were certain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:151350:72"/>
               <head>THE CONCLVSION to the Reader.</head>
               <p>GEntle Reader, out of all which hath been ſayd in this Treatiſe, I gather theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portants points which I much commend to thy memorye and conſideration. Firſt, that a <note place="margin">I.</note> ſufficientConfeſſor with paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall charge of ſouls, is more to the glorye of God, to the good of the Church, and to the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall profit of ſouls, then is a ſufficient Confeſſor, who hath no ſuch charge of ſouls. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <note place="margin">II.</note> that what good Prieſt ſeeketh the greater glorie of God, the greater good of the Church, and the greater ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall profit of ſouls, will more deſire to be a Confeſſor with
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:151350:72"/> charge of the ſouls of thoſe whoſe Confeſſions he heareth, then to be confeſſor without ſuch charge if conueniently he may be. Thirdly, that what <note place="margin">III.</note> Penitent ſeeketh the greater glorie of God, the greater good of the Church, and the greater ſpirituall profit of his ſoul, will vſe rather a ſufficient Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, who hath charge of his ſoul, then a ſufficient Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor who hath no ſuch charge of his ſoul if conueniently hee may. Fourthly, that if any should hinder or dehort from the making of Confeſſors with charge of ſouls, or counſel Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents to goe to others, rather then to ſuch, he should hinder and dehort from that, which is to the greater glorie of God, greater good of the Church, and greater ſpirituall profit of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:151350:73"/> ſouls which none can doe who ſeek the glorie of God, the good of the Church, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of ſoules. Which (I aſſure my ſelf) al good Prieſts in England doe really and hartily ſeek: and therefore I hope, that all ſuch, will take this my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of being confeſſors with charge of ſouls, in good parte; and wil if they can conuenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, follow it. Which if they doe, I shall hope of the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier conuerſion of our poore Countrye, in which are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye good sheep, but <hi>ſine pasto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus</hi> without paſtors; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are among woolues, need Paſtors more, then in Catholick Countryes, and need all ſpirituall help which may be had both by Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors with charge of ſouls, or without ſuch charge, as Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:151350:73"/> in Catholick Countryes haue. For my intention is not to depriue them of Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors without charge of ſouls, or of anye ſpirituall good, that can be gotten by ſuch, but to afford them both kindes of Confeſſors, as Penitents in Catholick Countryes, and in Ireland, and in Holland haue allſo, and to procure them all the ſpirituall good and help, which may be reaped by both ſuch Confeſſors.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
